<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Comedie of Errors.</title>
            <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <name>University of Oxford Text Archive</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Oxford University Computing Services</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>13 Banbury Road</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Oxford</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>OX2 6NN</addrLine>
               </address>
               <email>ota@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
            </distributor>
            <idno type="ota">http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/5702</idno>
            <idno type="isbn10">1106027019</idno>
            <idno type="isbn13">9781106027016</idno>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	Distributed by the University of Oxford under a Creative Commons
	Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
      </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Revised version of  <relatedItem type="older" target="http://ota.ox.ac.uk/id/0119"/>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>The texts were originally prepared by Trevor
	    Howard-Hill for use in his single volume concordances to
	    Shakespeare (OUP, 1969f). They have since been reformatted
	    to modern standards and carefully proofread by staff of
	    Oxford University Press' Shakespeare Department for use in
	    the new "Old Spelling" Oxford Shakespeare, under the
	    general editorship of Dr Stanley Wells: <title>The complete works
	    / William Shakespeare</title>; general editors, Stanley
	    Wells and Gary Taylor ; editors Stanley Wells ... [et al.]
	    ; with introductions by Stanley Wells. -- Oxford :
	    Clarendon Press, 1986. -- (Oxford Shakespeare). -- ISBN
	    0-19-812926-2</bibl>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Comedie of Errors.</title>
                  <author>Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616</author>
                  <editor role="editor">Lee, Sidney, Sir, 1859-1926</editor>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xxxv, 908 p. : facsims. ; 39 cm.</extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                  <date>1902</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note anchored="true">"One thousand copies of this facsimile have been printed"--verso of half t.p.</note>
                  <note anchored="true">Facsim. reprint of ed. published, London : printed by Issac Iaggard and Ed.[ward] Blount, 1623 with original t.p.: Mr. William Shakespeares comedies, histories, &amp; tragedies</note>
                  <note anchored="true">Original colophon reads: Printed at the charges of W.[illiam] Iaggard, Ed.[ward] Blount, I.[ohn] Smithweeke [i.e. Smethwick], and W.[illiam] Aspley, 1623</note>
                  <note anchored="true">Contents: The tempest. The two gentlemen of Verona. The merry wives of Windsor. Measvre, for measure. The comedie of errors. Much adoe about nothing. Loues labour's lost. A midsommer nights dreame. The merchant of Venice. As you like it. The taming of the shrew. All's well, that ends well. Twelfe night, or what you will. The winters tale. The life and death of King Iohn. The life and death of King Richard the second. The first part of Henry the fourth. The second part of Henry the fourth. The life of Henry the fift. The first part of Henry the sixt. The second part of Henry the sixt. The third part of Henry the sixt. The tragedy of Richard the third. The famous history of the life of King Henry the eight. The tragedie of Troylus and Cressida. The tragedy of Coriolanvs. The lamentable tragedy of Titus Andronicus. The tragedie of Romeo and Ivliet. The life of Tymon of Athens. The tragedie of Ivlivs Caesar. The tragedie of Macbeth. The tragedie of Hamlet, Prince of Denmarke. The tragedie of King Lear. The tragedie of Othello, the moore of Venice. The tragedie of Anthonie, and Cleopatra. The tragedie of Cymbeline</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <charDecl>
            <glyph xml:id="ythou">
               <glyphName>Lower case y with smaller lower case u above</glyphName>
               <desc>Abbreviation for thou in Elizabethan
	    typesetting</desc>
               <charProp>
                  <localName>entity</localName>
                  <value>ythou</value>
               </charProp>
            </glyph>
            <glyph xml:id="ythe">
               <glyphName>Lower case y with smaller lower case e above</glyphName>
               <desc>Abbreviation for the in Elizabethan typesetting</desc>
               <charProp>
                  <localName>entity</localName>
                  <value>ythe</value>
               </charProp>
            </glyph>
            <glyph xml:id="ythat">
               <glyphName>Lower case y with smaller lower case t above</glyphName>
               <desc>Abbreviation for that in Elizabethan typesetting</desc>
               <charProp>
                  <localName>entity</localName>
                  <value>ythat</value>
               </charProp>
            </glyph>
            <glyph xml:id="wwhich">
               <glyphName>Lower case w with smaller lower case c above</glyphName>
               <desc>Abbreviation for which in Elizabethan typesetting</desc>
               <charProp>
                  <localName>entity</localName>
                  <value>wwhich</value>
               </charProp>
            </glyph>
         </charDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="OTASH">
               <bibl>University of Oxford Text Archive Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notAfter="1623"/>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <term type="genre">Plays -- England -- 16th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Plays -- England -- 17th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Comedies -- England -- 16th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Comedies -- England -- 17th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Tragedies -- England -- 16th century</term>
               <term type="genre">Tragedies -- England -- 17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2010-08-31">Header normalised</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
          <pb n="H1"/>
          <head>The Comedie of Errors.</head>
          <milestone unit="compo" n="C"/>
          <lb n="1"/>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic">Actus primus, Scena prima.</head>
            <lb n="2" rend="rj"/>
            <stage rend="italic">Enter the Duke of Ephesus, with the Merchant of Siracusa,<lb n="3"/>Iaylor, and other attendants.</stage>
            <lb n="4"/>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Marchant.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <lb n="5"/>Proceed <hi rend="italic">Solinus</hi> to procure my fall,<lb n="6" rend="rj"/>And by the doome of death end woes and all.<lb n="7" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Merchant of <hi rend="italic">Siracusa,</hi> plead no more.<lb n="8"/>I am not partiall to infringe our Lawes;<lb n="9"/>The enmity and discord which of late<lb n="10"/>Sprung from the rancorous outrage of your Duke,<lb n="11"/>To Merchants our well-dealing Countrimen,<lb n="12"/>Who wanting gilders to redeeme their liues,<lb n="13"/>Haue seal'd his rigorous statutes with their blouds,<lb n="14"/>Excludes all pitty from our threatning lookes:<lb n="15"/>For since the mortall and intestine iarres<lb n="16"/>Twixt thy seditious Countrimen and vs,<lb n="17"/>It hath in solemne Synodes beene decreed,<lb n="18"/>Both by the <hi rend="italic">Siracusians</hi> and our selues,<lb n="19"/>To admit no trafficke to our aduerse townes:<lb n="20"/>Nay more, if any borne at <hi rend="italic">Ephesus</hi>
                        <lb n="21"/>Be seene at any <hi rend="italic">Siracusian</hi> Marts and Fayres:<lb n="22"/>Againe, if any <hi rend="italic">Siracusian</hi> borne<lb n="23"/>Come to the Bay of <hi rend="italic">Ephesus,</hi> he dies:<lb n="24"/>His goods confiscate to the Dukes dispose,<lb n="25"/>Vnlesse a thousand markes be leuied<lb n="26"/>To quit the penalty, and to ransome him:<lb n="27"/>Thy substance, valued at the highest rate,<lb n="28"/>Cannot amount vnto a hundred Markes,<lb n="29"/>Therefore by Law thou art condemn'd to die.<lb n="30" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mer.</speaker>
              <ab>Yet this my comfort, when your words are done,<lb n="31"/>My woes end likewise with the euening Sonne.<lb n="32"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duk.</speaker>
              <ab>Well <hi rend="italic">Siracusian;</hi> say in briefe the cause<lb n="33"/>Why thou departedst from thy natiue home?<lb n="34"/>And for what cause thou cam'st to <hi rend="italic">Ephesus.</hi>
                        <lb n="35" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mer.</speaker>
              <ab>A heauier taske could not haue beene impos'd,<lb n="36"/>Then I to speake my griefes vnspeakeable:<lb n="37"/>Yet that the world may witnesse that my end<lb n="38"/>Was wrought by nature, not by vile offence,<lb n="39"/>Ile vtter what my sorrow giues me leaue.<lb n="40"/>In <hi rend="italic">Syracusa</hi> was I borne, and wedde<lb n="41"/>Vnto a woman, happy but for me,<lb n="42"/>And by me; had not our hap beene bad:<lb n="43"/>With her I liu'd in ioy, our wealth increast<lb n="44"/>By prosperous voyages I often made<lb n="45"/>To <hi rend="italic">Epidamium,</hi> till my factors death,<lb n="46"/>And he great care of goods at randone left,<lb n="47"/>Drew me from kinde embracements of my spouse;<lb n="48"/>From whom my absence was not sixe moneths olde,<lb n="49"/>Before her selfe (almost at fainting vnder<lb n="50"/>The pleasing punishment that women beare)<lb n="51"/>Had made prouision for her following me,<lb n="52"/>And soone, and safe, arriued where I was:<lb n="53"/>There had she not beene long, but she became<lb n="54"/>A ioyfull mother of two goodly sonnes:<lb n="55"/>And, which was strange, the one so like the other,<lb n="56"/>As could not be distinguish'd but by names.<lb n="57"/>That very howre, and in the selfe-same Inne,<lb n="58"/>A meane woman was deliuered<lb n="59"/>Of such a burthen Male, twins both alike:<lb n="60"/>Those, for their parents were exceeding poore,<lb n="61"/>I bought, and brought vp to attend my sonnes.<lb n="62"/>My wife, not meanely prowd of two such boyes,<lb n="63"/>Made daily motions for our home returne:<lb n="64"/>Vnwilling I agreed, alas, too soone wee came aboord.<lb n="65"/>A league from <hi rend="italic">Epidamium</hi> had we saild<lb n="66"/>Before the alwaies winde-obeying deepe<lb n="67"/>Gaue any Tragicke Instance of our harme:<lb n="68"/>But longer did we not retaine much hope;<lb n="69"/>For what obscured light the heauens did grant,<lb n="70"/>Did but conuay vnto our fearefull mindes<lb n="71"/>A doubtfull warrant of immediate death,<lb n="72"/>Which though my selfe would gladly haue imbrac'd,<lb n="73"/>Yet the incessant weepings of my wife,<lb n="74"/>Weeping before for what she saw must come,<lb n="75"/>And pitteous playnings of the prettie babes<lb n="76"/>That mourn'd for fashion, ignorant what to feare,<lb n="77"/>Forst me to seeke delayes for them and me,<lb n="78"/>And this it was: (for other meanes was none)<lb n="79"/>The Sailors sought for safety by our boate,<lb n="80"/>And left the ship then sinking ripe to vs.<lb n="81"/>My wife, more carefull for the latter borne,<lb n="82"/>Had fastned him vnto a small spare Mast,<lb n="83"/>Such as sea-faring men prouide for stormes:<lb n="84"/>To him one of the other twins was bound,<lb n="85"/>Whil'st I had beene like heedfull of the other.<lb n="86"/>The children thus dispos'd, my wife and I,<lb n="87"/>Fixing our eyes on whom our care was fixt,<lb n="88"/>Fastned our selues at eyther end the mast,<lb n="89"/>And floating straight, obedient to the streame,<lb n="90"/>Was carried towards <hi rend="italic">Corinth,</hi> as we thought.<lb n="91"/>At length the sonne gazing vpon the earth,<lb n="92"/>Disperst those vapours that offended vs,<lb n="93"/>And by the benefit of his wished light<lb n="94"/>The seas waxt calme, and we discouered<lb n="95"/>Two shippes from farre, making amaine to vs:<lb n="96"/>Of <hi rend="italic">Corinth</hi> that, of <hi rend="italic">Epidarus</hi> this,<lb n="97"/>But ere they came, oh let me say no more,<lb n="98"/>Gather the sequell by that went before.<lb n="99"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duk.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay forward old man, doe not breake off so,
      <pb n="H1v"/>
                        <lb n="100"/>For we may pitty, though not pardon thee.<lb n="101"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Merch.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh had the gods done so, I had not now<lb n="102"/>Worthily tearm'd them mercilesse to vs:<lb n="103"/>For ere the ships could meet by twice fiue leagues,<lb n="104"/>We were encountred by a mighty rocke,<lb n="105"/>Which being violently borne vp,<lb n="106"/>Our helpefull ship was splitted in the midst;<lb n="107"/>So that in this vniust diuorce of vs,<lb n="108"/>Fortune had left to both of vs alike,<lb n="109"/>What to delight in, what to sorrow for,<lb n="110"/>Her part, poore soule, seeming as burdened<lb n="111"/>With lesser waight, but not with lesser woe,<lb n="112"/>Was carried with more speed before the winde,<lb n="113"/>And in our sight they three were taken vp<lb n="114"/>By Fishermen of <hi rend="italic">Corinth,</hi> as we thought.<lb n="115"/>At length another ship had seiz'd on vs,<lb n="116"/>And knowing whom it was their hap to saue,<lb n="117"/>Gaue healthfull welcome to their ship-wrackt guests,<lb n="118"/>And would haue reft the Fishers of their prey,<lb n="119"/>Had not their backe beene very slow of saile;<lb n="120"/>And therefore homeward did they bend their course.<lb n="121"/>Thus haue you heard me seuer'd from my blisse,<lb n="122"/>That by misfortunes was my life prolong'd,<lb n="123"/>To tell sad stories of my owne mishaps.<lb n="124"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>And for the sake of them thou sorrowest for,<lb n="125"/>Doe me the fauour to dilate at full,<lb n="126"/>What haue befalne of them and they till now.<lb n="127"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Merch.</speaker>
              <ab>My yongest boy, and yet my eldest care,<lb n="128"/>At eighteene yeeres became inquisitiue<lb n="129"/>After his brother; and importun'd me<lb n="130"/>That his attendant, so his case was like,<lb n="131"/>Reft of his brother, but retain'd his name,<lb n="132"/>Might beare him company in the quest of him:<lb n="133"/>Whom whil'st I laboured of a loue to see,<lb n="134"/>I hazarded the losse of whom I lou'd.<lb n="135"/>Fiue Sommers haue I spent in farthest <hi rend="italic">Greece,</hi>
                        <lb n="136"/>Roming cleane through the bounds of <hi rend="italic">Asia,</hi>
                        <lb n="137"/>And coasting homeward, came to <hi rend="italic">Ephesus:</hi>
                        <lb n="138"/>Hopelesse to finde, yet loth to leaue vnsought<lb n="139"/>Or that, or any place that harbours men:<lb n="140"/>But heere must end the story of my life,<lb n="141"/>And happy were I in my timelie death,<lb n="142"/>Could all my trauells warrant me they liue.<lb n="143"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Haplesse <hi rend="italic">Egeon</hi> whom the fates haue markt<lb n="144"/>To beare the extremitie of dire mishap:<lb n="145"/>Now trust me, were it not against our Lawes,<lb n="146"/>Against my Crowne, my oath, my dignity,<lb n="147"/>Which Princes would they may not disanull,<lb n="148"/>My soule should sue as aduocate for thee:<lb n="149"/>But though  thou art adiudged to the death,<lb n="150"/>And passed sentence may not be recal'd<lb n="151"/>But to our honours great disparagement:<lb n="152"/>Yet will I fauour thee in what I can;<lb n="153"/>Therefore Marchant, Ile limit thee this day<lb n="154"/>To seeke thy helpe by beneficiall helpe,<lb n="155"/>Try all the friends thou hast in <hi rend="italic">Ephesus,</hi>
                        <lb n="156"/>Beg thou, or borrow, to make vp the summe,<lb n="157"/>And liue: if no, then thou art doom'd to die:<lb n="158"/>Iaylor, take him to thy custodie.<lb n="159"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Iaylor.</speaker>
              <ab>I will my Lord.<lb n="160"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Merch.</speaker>
              <ab>Hopelesse and helpelesse doth <hi rend="italic">Egean</hi> wend,<lb n="161"/>But to procrastinate his liuelesse end.  <stage rend="italic">Exeunt.</stage>
                        <lb n="162"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholis Erotes, a Marchant, and Dromio.</stage>
                        <lb n="163"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mer.</speaker>
              <ab>Therefore giue out you are of <hi rend="italic">Epidamium,</hi>
                        <lb n="164"/>Lest that your goods too soone be confiscate:
      <milestone unit="compo" n="D"/>
                        <lb n="165"/>This very day a <hi rend="italic">Syracusian</hi> Marchant<lb n="166"/>Is apprehended for a riuall here,<lb n="167"/>And not being able to buy out his life,<lb n="168"/>According to the statute of the towne,<lb n="169"/>Dies ere the wearie sunne set in the West:<lb n="170"/>There is your monie that I had to keepe.<lb n="171"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Goe beare it to the Centaure, where we host,<lb n="172"/>And stay there <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> till I come to thee;<lb n="173"/>Within this houre it will be dinner time,<lb n="174"/>Till that Ile view the manners of the towne,<lb n="175"/>Peruse the traders, gaze vpon the buildings,<lb n="176"/>And then returne and sleepe within mine Inne,<lb n="177"/>For with long trauaile I am stiffe and wearie.<lb n="178"/>Get thee away.<lb n="179"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Many a man would take you at your word,<lb n="180"/>And goe indeede, hauing so good a meane.<lb n="181"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exit Dromio.</stage>
                        <lb n="182"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>A trustie villaine sir, that very oft,<lb n="183"/>When I am dull with care and melancholly,<lb n="184"/>Lightens my humour with his merry iests:<lb n="185"/>What will you walke with me about the towne,<lb n="186"/>And then goe to my Inne and dine with me?<lb n="187"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>I am inuited sir to certaine Marchants,<lb n="188"/>Of whom I hope to make much benefit:<lb n="189"/>I craue your pardon, soone at fiue <seg type="homograph">a</seg> clocke,<lb n="190"/>Please you, Ile meete with you vpon the Mart,<lb n="191"/>And afterward consort you till bed time:<lb n="192"/>My present businesse cals me from you now.<lb n="193"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Farewell till then: I will goe loose my selfe,<lb n="194"/>And wander vp and downe to view the Citie.<lb n="195" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>Sir, I commend you to your owne content.<lb n="196"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt.</stage>
                        <lb n="197"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>He that commends me to mine owne content,<lb n="198"/>Commends me to the thing I cannot get:<lb n="199"/>I to the world am like a drop of water,<lb n="200"/>That in the Ocean seekes another drop,<lb n="201"/>Who falling there to finde his fellow forth,<lb n="202"/>(Vnseene, inquisitiue) confounds himselfe.<lb n="203"/>So I, to finde a Mother and a Brother,<lb n="204"/>In quest of them (vnhappie <seg type="homograph">a</seg>) loose my selfe.<lb n="205"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio of Ephesus.</stage>
                        <lb n="206"/>Here comes the almanacke of my true date:<lb n="207"/>What now? How chance thou art return'd so soone.<lb n="208" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Return'd so soone, rather approacht too late:<lb n="209"/>The Capon burnes, the Pig fals from the spit;<lb n="210"/>The clocke hath strucken twelue vpon the bell:<lb n="211"/>My Mistris made it one vpon my cheeke:<lb n="212"/>She is so hot because the meate is colde:<lb n="213"/>The meate is colde, because you come not home:<lb n="214"/>You come not home, because you haue no stomacke:<lb n="215"/>You haue no stomacke, hauing broke your fast:<lb n="216"/>But we that know what 'tis to fast and pray,<lb n="217"/>Are penitent for your default to day.<lb n="218"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Stop in your winde sir, tell me this I pray?<lb n="219"/>Where haue you left the mony that I gaue you.<lb n="220"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh sixe pence that I had <seg type="homograph">a</seg> wensday last,<lb n="221"/>To pay the Sadler for my Mistris crupper:<lb n="222"/>The Sadler had it Sir, I kept it not.<lb n="223"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I am not in a sportiue humor now:<lb n="224"/>Tell me, and dally not, where is the monie?<lb n="225"/>We being strangers here, how dar'st thou trust<lb n="226"/>So great a charge from thine owne custodie.<lb n="227"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I pray you iest sir as you sit at dinner:<lb n="228"/>I from my Mistris come to you in post:<lb n="229"/>If I returne I shall be post indeede.
      <pb n="H2"/>
                        <lb n="230"/>For she will scoure your fault vpon my pate:<lb n="231" rend="rj"/>Me thinkes your maw, like mine, should be your cooke,<lb n="232"/>And strike you home without a messenger.<lb n="233" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Come <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> come, these iests are out of season,<lb n="234"/>Reserue them till a merrier houre then this:<lb n="235"/>Where is the gold I gaue in charge to thee?<lb n="236"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>To me sir? why you gaue no gold to me?<lb n="237" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Come on sir knaue, haue done your foolishnes,<lb n="238"/>And tell me how thou hast dispos'd thy charge.<lb n="239" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>My charge was but to fetch you fro[m] the Mart<lb n="240"/>Home to your house, the <hi rend="italic">Phoenix</hi> sir, to dinner;<lb n="241"/>My Mistris and her sister staies for you.<lb n="242"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Now as I am a Christian answer me,<lb n="243"/>In what safe place you haue bestow'd my monie;<lb n="244"/>Or I shall breake that merrie sconce of yours<lb n="245"/>That stands on tricks, when I am vndispos'd:<lb n="246"/>Where is the thousand Markes thou hadst of me?<lb n="247"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I haue some markes of yours vpon my pate:<lb n="248"/>Some of my Mistris markes vpon my shoulders:<lb n="249"/>But not a thousand markes betweene you both.<lb n="250"/>If I should pay your worship those againe,<lb n="251"/>Perchance you will not beare them patiently.<lb n="252" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thy Mistris markes? what Mistris slaue hast thou?<lb n="253" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Your worships wife, my Mistris at the <hi rend="italic">Phoenix;</hi>
                        <lb n="254"/>She that doth fast till you come home to dinner:<lb n="255"/>And praies that you will hie you home to dinner.<lb n="256"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>What wilt thou flout me thus vnto my face<lb n="257"/>Being forbid? There take you that sir knaue.<lb n="258" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>What meane you sir, for God sake hold your <seg type="carryOver">hands</seg>:<lb n="259"/>Nay, <seg type="homograph">and</seg> you will not sir, Ile take my heeles.<lb n="260"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt Dromio Ep.</stage>
                        <lb n="261"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Vpon my life by some deuise or other,<lb n="262"/>The villaine is ore-wrought of all my monie.<lb n="263"/>They say this towne is full of cosenage:<lb n="264"/>As nimble Iuglers that deceiue the eie:<lb n="265"/>Darke working Sorcerers that change the minde:<lb n="266"/>Soule-killing  Witches, that deforme the bodie:<lb n="267"/>Disguised Cheaters, prating Mountebankes;<lb n="268"/>And manie such like liberties of sinne:<lb n="269"/>If it proue so, I will be gone the sooner:<lb n="270"/>Ile to the Centaur to goe seeke this slaue,<lb n="271"/>I greatly feare my monie is not safe.  <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="272"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic">Actus Secundus.</head>
            <lb n="273"/>
            <stage rend="italic">Enter Adriana, wife to Antipholis Sereptus, with<lb n="274"/>Luciana her Sister.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Neither my husband nor the slaue return'd,<lb n="276"/>That in such haste I sent to seeke his Master?<lb n="277"/>Sure <hi rend="italic">Luciana</hi> it is two <seg type="homograph">a</seg> clocke.<lb n="278"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Perhaps some Merchant hath inuited him,<lb n="279"/>And from the Mart he's somewhere  gone to dinner:<lb n="280"/>Good Sister let vs dine, and neuer fret;<lb n="281"/>A man is Master of his libertie:<lb n="282"/>Time is their Master, and when they see time,<lb n="283"/>They'll goe or come; if so, be patient Sister.<lb n="284" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Why should their libertie then ours be more?<lb n="285"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Because their businesse still lies out <seg type="homograph">a</seg>
                        <seg type="homograph">dore</seg>.<lb n="286"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Looke when I serue him so, he takes it thus.<lb n="287"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh, know he is the bridle of your <seg type="homograph">will</seg>.<lb n="288"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>There's none but asses will be bridled so.
      <milestone unit="compo" n="C"/>
                        <lb n="289"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Why, headstrong liberty is lasht with woe:<lb n="290"/>There's nothing situate vnder heauens eye,<lb n="291"/>But hath his bound in earth, in sea, in skie.<lb n="292"/>The beasts, the fishes, and the winged fowles<lb n="293"/>Are their males subiects, and at their controules:<lb n="294"/>Man more diuine, the Master of all these,<lb n="295"/>Lord of the wide world, and wilde watry seas,<lb n="296"/>Indued with intellectuall sence and soules,<lb n="297"/>Of more preheminence then fish and fowles,<lb n="298"/>Are masters to their females, and their Lords:<lb n="299"/>Then let your <seg type="homograph">will</seg> attend on their accords.<lb n="300"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>This seruitude makes you to keepe vnwed.<lb n="301"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>Not this, but troubles of the marriage bed.<lb n="302" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>But were you wedded, you wold bear some sway<lb n="303"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Ere I learne loue, Ile practise to obey.<lb n="304"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>How if your husband start some other where?<lb n="305"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Till he come home againe, I would forbeare.<lb n="306" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Patience vnmou'd, no maruel though she pause,<lb n="307"/>They can be meeke, that haue no other cause:<lb n="308"/>A wretched soule bruis'd with aduersitie,<lb n="309"/>We bid be quiet when we heare it crie.<lb n="310"/>But were we burdned with like waight of paine,<lb n="311"/>As much, or more, we should our selues complaine:<lb n="312"/>So thou that hast no vnkinde mate to greeue thee,<lb n="313"/>With vrging helpelesse patience would releeue me;<lb n="314"/>But if thou liue to see like right bereft,<lb n="315"/>This foole-beg'd patience in thee will be left.<lb n="316"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>Well, I will marry one day but to trie:<lb n="317"/>Heere comes your man, now is your husband nie.<lb n="318"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio Eph.</stage>
                        <lb n="319"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Say, is your tardie master now at hand?<lb n="320" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay, hee's at <seg type="homograph">too</seg> hands with mee, and that my<lb n="321"/>two eares can witnesse.<lb n="322" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Say, didst thou speake with him? knowst thou<lb n="323"/>his minde?<lb n="324"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, he told his minde vpon mine eare,<lb n="325"/>Beshrew his hand, I scarce could vnderstand it.<lb n="326" rend="rj"/>
               </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Spake hee so doubtfully, thou couldst not feele<lb n="327"/>his meaning.<lb n="328" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay, hee strooke so plainly, I could too well<lb n="329" rend="rj"/>feele his blowes; and withall so doubtfully, that I could<lb n="330"/>scarce vnderstand them.<lb n="331"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>But say, I prethee, is he comming home?<lb n="332"/>It seemes he hath great care to please his wife.<lb n="333" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Why Mistresse, sure my Master is horne mad.<lb n="334"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>Horne mad, thou villaine?<lb n="335"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I meane not Cuckold mad,<lb n="336"/>But sure he is starke mad:<lb n="337"/>When I desir'd him to come home to dinner,<lb n="338"/>He ask'd me for a hundred markes in gold:<lb n="339"/>'Tis dinner time, quoth I: my gold, quoth he:<lb n="340"/>Your meat doth burne, quoth I: my gold quoth he:<lb n="341"/>Will you come, quoth I: my gold, quoth he;<lb n="342"/>Where is the thousand markes I gaue thee villaine?<lb n="343"/>The Pigge quoth I, is burn'd: my gold, quoth he:<lb n="344"/>My mistresse, sir, quoth I: hang vp thy Mistresse:<lb n="345"/>I know not thy mistresse, out on thy mistresse.<lb n="346"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>Quoth who?<lb n="347" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dr.</speaker>
              <ab>Quoth my Master, I know quoth he, no house,<lb n="348" rend="rj"/>no wife, no mistresse: so that my arrant due vnto my<lb n="349" rend="rj"/>tongue, I thanke him, I bare home vpon my shoulders:<lb n="350"/>for in conclusion, he did beat me there.<lb n="351" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>Go back againe, thou slaue, &amp; fetch him home.<lb n="352"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Goe backe againe, and be new beaten home?<lb n="353"/>For Gods sake send some other messenger.
      <pb n="H2v"/>
                        <lb n="354" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>Backe slaue, or I will breake thy pate a-crosse.<lb n="355" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>And he will blesse <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythe"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>the</reg>
                  </choice> crosse with other beating:<lb n="356"/>Betweene you, I shall haue a holy head.<lb n="357"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>Hence prating pesant, fetch thy Master home.<lb n="358"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Am I so round with you, as you with me,<lb n="359"/>That like a foot-ball you doe spurne me thus:<lb n="360"/>You spurne me hence, and he will spurne me hither,<lb n="361"/>If I last in this seruice, you must case me in leather.<lb n="362"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>Fie how impatience lowreth in your face.<lb n="363"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>His company must do his minions grace,<lb n="364"/>Whil'st I at home starue for a merrie looke:<lb n="365"/>Hath homelie age th' alluring beauty tooke<lb n="366"/>From my poore cheeke? then he hath wasted it.<lb n="367"/>Are my discourses dull? Barren my wit,<lb n="368"/>If voluble and sharpe discourse be mar'd,<lb n="369"/>Vnkindnesse blunts it more then marble hard.<lb n="370"/>Doe their gay vestments his affections baite?<lb n="371"/>That's not my fault, hee's master of my state.<lb n="372"/>What ruines are in me that can be found,<lb n="373"/>By him not ruin'd? Then is he the ground<lb n="374"/>Of my defeatures. My decayed faire,<lb n="375"/>A sunnie looke of his, would soone repaire.<lb n="376"/>But, too vnruly Deere, he breakes the pale,<lb n="377"/>And feedes from home; poore I am but his stale.<lb n="378"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>Selfe-harming Iealousie; fie beat it hence.<lb n="379" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ad.</speaker>
              <ab>Vnfeeling fools can with such wrongs dispence:<lb n="380"/>I know his eye doth homage other-where,<lb n="381"/>Or else, what lets it but he would be here?<lb n="382"/>Sister, you know he promis'd me a chaine,<lb n="383"/>Would that alone, a loue he would detaine,<lb n="384"/>So he would keepe faire quarter with his bed:<lb n="385"/>I see the Iewell best enamaled<lb n="386"/>Will loose his beautie: yet the gold bides still<lb n="387"/>That others touch, and often touching will,<lb n="388"/>Where gold and no man that hath a name,<lb n="389"/>By falshood and corruption doth it shame:<lb n="390"/>Since that my beautie cannot please his eie,<lb n="391"/>Ile weepe (what's left away) and weeping die.<lb n="392"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>How manie fond fooles serue mad Ielousie?<lb n="393"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="394"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholis Errotis.</stage>
                        <lb n="395"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>The gold I gaue to <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> is laid vp<lb n="396"/>Safe at the <hi rend="italic">Centaur,</hi> and the heedfull slaue<lb n="397"/>Is wandred forth in care to seeke me out<lb n="398"/>By computation and mine hosts report.<lb n="399"/>I could not speake with <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> since at first<lb n="400"/>I sent him from the Mart? see here he comes.<lb n="401"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio Siracusia.</stage>
                        <lb n="402"/>How now sir, is your merrie humor alter'd?<lb n="403"/>As you loue stroakes, so iest with me againe:<lb n="404"/>You know no <hi rend="italic">Centaur</hi>? you receiu'd no gold?<lb n="405"/>Your Mistresse sent to haue me home to dinner?<lb n="406"/>My house was at the <hi rend="italic">Phoenix</hi>? Wast thou mad,<lb n="407"/>That thus so madlie thou did didst answere me?<lb n="408"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>What answer sir? when spake I such a word?<lb n="409" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Euen now, euen here, not halfe an howre since.<lb n="410"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I did not see you since you sent me hence<lb n="411"/>Home to the <hi rend="italic">Centaur</hi> with the gold you gaue me.<lb n="412"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Villaine, thou didst denie the golds receit,<lb n="413"/>And toldst me of a Mistresse, and a dinner,<lb n="414"/>For which I hope thou feltst I was displeas'd.<lb n="415"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I am glad to see you in this merrie vaine,<lb n="416"/>What meanes this iest, I pray you Master tell me?<lb n="417"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Yea, dost thou ieere &amp; flowt me in the teeth?<lb n="418" rend="rj"/>Thinkst <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythou"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>thou</reg>
                  </choice> I iest? hold, take thou that, &amp; that.  <stage rend="italic">Beats Dro.</stage>
                        <lb n="419" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dr.</speaker>
              <ab>Hold sir, for Gods sake, now your iest is earnest,<lb n="420"/>Vpon what bargaine do you giue it me?<lb n="421"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Antiph.</speaker>
              <ab>Because that I familiarlie sometimes<lb n="422"/>Doe vse you for my foole, and chat with you,<lb n="423"/>Your sawcinesse will iest vpon my loue,<lb n="424"/>And make a Common of my serious howres,<lb n="425"/>When the sunne shines, let foolish gnats make sport,<lb n="426"/>But creepe in crannies, when he hides his beames:<lb n="427"/>If you will iest with me, know my aspect,<lb n="428"/>And fashion your demeanor to my lookes,<lb n="429"/>Or I will beat this method in your sconce.<lb n="430" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Sconce call you it? so you would leaue batte-<lb type="inWord" n="431" rend="rj"/>ring, I had rather haue it a head, <seg type="homograph">and</seg> you vse these blows<lb n="432" rend="rj"/>long, I must get a sconce for my head, and Insconce it<lb n="433" rend="rj"/>
                        <seg type="homograph">to</seg>, or else I shall seek my wit in my shoulders, but I pray<lb n="434"/>sir, why am I beaten?<lb n="435"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Dost thou not know?<lb n="436"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nothing sir, but that I am beaten.<lb n="437"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Shall I tell you <seg type="homograph">why</seg>?<lb n="438" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg> sir, and wherefore; for they say, euery <seg type="homograph">why</seg>
                        <lb n="439"/>hath a wherefore.<lb n="440" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">Why</seg> first for flowting me, and then wherefore,<lb n="441"/>for vrging it the second time to me.<lb n="442" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Was there euer anie man thus beaten out of<lb n="443" rend="rj"/>season, when in the <seg type="homograph">why</seg> and the wherefore, is neither<lb n="444"/>rime nor reason. Well sir, I thanke you.<lb n="445"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thanke me sir, for what?<lb n="446" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry sir, for this something that you gaue me<lb n="447"/>for nothing.<lb n="448" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Ile make you amends next, to giue you nothing<lb n="449"/>for something. But say sir, is it dinner time?<lb n="450"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No sir, I thinke the meat wants that I haue.<lb n="451"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>In good time sir: what's that?<lb n="452"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Basting.<lb n="453"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Well sir, then 'twill be drie.<lb n="454"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>If it be sir, I pray you eat none of it.<lb n="455"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Your reason?<lb n="456" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Lest it make you chollericke, and purchase me<lb n="457"/>another drie basting.<lb n="458" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Well sir, learne to iest in good time, there's a<lb n="459"/>time for all things.<lb n="460" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I durst haue denied that before you were so<lb n="461"/>chollericke.<lb n="462"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>By what rule sir?<lb n="463" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry sir, by a rule as plaine as the plaine bald<lb n="464"/>pate of Father time himselfe.<lb n="465"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Let's heare it.<lb n="466" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>There's no time for a man to recouer his haire<lb n="467"/>that growes bald by nature.<lb n="468"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>May he not doe it by fine and recouerie?<lb n="469" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Yes, to pay a fine for a perewig, and recouer<lb n="470"/>the lost haire of another man.<lb n="471" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Why, is Time such a niggard of haire, being (as<lb n="472"/>it is) so plentifull an excrement?<lb n="473" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Because it is a blessing that hee bestowes on<lb n="474" rend="rj"/>beasts, and what he hath scanted them in haire, hee hath<lb n="475"/>giuen them in wit.<lb n="476" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Why, but theres manie a man hath more haire<lb n="477"/>then wit.<lb n="478" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Not a man of those but he hath the wit to lose<lb n="479"/>his haire.<lb n="480" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Why thou didst conclude hairy men plain dea-<lb n="481" type="inWord"/>lers without wit.<lb n="482" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>The plainer dealer, the sooner lost; yet he loo-<lb n="483" type="inWord"/>seth it in a kinde of iollitie.<lb n="484"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>For what reason.<lb n="485"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>For two, and sound ones <seg type="homograph">to</seg>.
      <pb n="H3"/>
                        <lb n="486"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay not sound I pray you.<lb n="487"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Sure ones then.<lb n="488"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay, not sure in a thing falsing.<lb n="489"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Certaine ones then.<lb n="490"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>Name them.<lb n="491" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>The one to saue the money that he spends in<lb n="492" rend="rj"/>trying: the other, that at dinner they should not drop in<lb n="493"/>his porrage.<lb n="494" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>You would all this time haue prou'd, there is no<lb n="495"/>time for all things.<lb n="496" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry and did sir: namely, in no time to re-<lb n="497" type="inWord"/>couer haire lost by Nature.<lb n="498" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>But your reason was not substantiall, why there<lb n="499"/>is no time to recouer.<lb n="500" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Thus I mend it: Time himselfe is bald, and<lb n="501"/>therefore to the worlds end, will haue bald followers.<lb n="502" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>I knew 'twould be a bald conclusion: but soft,<lb n="503"/>who wafts vs yonder.<lb n="504"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Adriana and Luciana.</stage>
                        <lb n="505"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, <hi rend="italic">Antipholus,</hi> looke strange and frowne,<lb n="506"/>Some other Mistresse hath thy sweet aspects:<lb n="507"/>I am not <hi rend="italic">Adriana,</hi> nor thy wife.<lb n="508"/>The time was once, when thou vn-vrg'd wouldst vow,<lb n="509"/>That neuer words were musicke to thine eare,<lb n="510"/>That neuer obiect pleasing in thine eye,<lb n="511"/>That neuer touch well welcome to thy hand,<lb n="512"/>That neuer meat sweet-sauour'd in thy taste,<lb n="513"/>Vnlesse I spake, or look'd, or touch'd, or caru'd to thee.<lb n="514"/>How comes it now, my Husband, oh how comes it,<lb n="515"/>That thou art then estranged from thy selfe?<lb n="516"/>Thy selfe I call it, being strange to me:<lb n="517"/>That vndiuidable Incorporate<lb n="518"/>Am better then thy deere selfes better part.<lb n="519"/>Ah doe not teare away thy selfe from me;<lb n="520"/>For know my loue: as easie maist thou fall<lb n="521"/>A drop of water in the breaking gulfe,<lb n="522"/>And take vnmingled thence that drop againe<lb n="523"/>Without addition or diminishing,<lb n="524"/>As take from me thy selfe, and not me too.<lb n="525"/>How deerely would it touch thee to the quicke,<lb n="526"/>Shouldst thou but heare I were licencious?<lb n="527"/>And that this body consecrate to thee,<lb n="528"/>By Ruffian Lust should be contaminate?<lb n="529"/>Wouldst thou not spit at me, and spurne at me,<lb n="530"/>And hurle the name of husband in my face,<lb n="531"/>And teare the stain'd skin of my Harlot brow,<lb n="532"/>And from my false hand cut the wedding ring,<lb n="533"/>And breake it with a deepe-diuorcing vow?<lb n="534"/>I know thou canst, and therefore see thou doe it.<lb n="535"/>I am possest with an adulterate blot,<lb n="536"/>My bloud is mingled with the crime of lust:<lb n="537"/>For if we two be one, and thou play false,<lb n="538"/>I doe digest the poison of thy flesh,<lb n="539"/>Being strumpeted by thy contagion:<lb n="540"/>Keepe then faire league and truce with thy true bed,<lb n="541"/>I liue distain'd, thou vndishonoured.<lb n="542" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Antip.</speaker>
              <ab>Plead you to me faire dame? I know you not:<lb n="543"/>In <hi rend="italic">Ephesus</hi> I am but two houres old,<lb n="544"/>As strange vnto your towne, as to your talke,<lb n="545"/>Who euery word by all my wit being scan'd,<lb n="546"/>Wants wit in all, one word to vnderstand.<lb n="547" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>Fie brother, how the world is chang'd with you:<lb n="548"/>When were you wont to vse my sister thus?<lb n="549"/>She sent for you by <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> home to dinner.
      <milestone unit="compo" n="D"/>
                        <lb n="550"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>By <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi>? </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Drom.</speaker>
              <ab>By me.<lb n="551" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>By thee, and this thou didst returne from him.<lb n="552"/>That he did buffet thee, and in his blowes,<lb n="553"/>Denied my house for his, me for his wife.<lb n="554"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Did you conuerse sir with this gentlewoman:<lb n="555"/>What is the course and drift of your compact?<lb n="556"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I sir? I neuer saw her till this time.<lb n="557"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Villaine thou liest, for euen her verie words,<lb n="558"/>Didst thou deliuer to me on the Mart.<lb n="559"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I neuer spake with her in all my life.<lb n="560"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>How can she thus then call vs by our names?<lb n="561"/>Vnlesse it be by inspiration.<lb n="562"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>How <seg type="homograph">ill</seg> agrees it with your grauitie,<lb n="563"/>To counterfeit thus grosely with your slaue,<lb n="564"/>Abetting him to thwart me in my moode;<lb n="565"/>Be it my wrong, you are from me exempt,<lb n="566"/>But wrong not that wrong with a more contempt.<lb n="567"/>Come I will fasten on this sleeue of thine:<lb n="568"/>Thou art an Elme my husband, I a Vine:<lb n="569"/>Whose weaknesse married to thy stranger state,<lb n="570"/>Makes me with thy strength to communicate:<lb n="571"/>If ought possesse thee from me, it is drosse,<lb n="572"/>Vsurping Iuie, Brier, or idle Mosse,<lb n="573"/>Who all for want of pruning, with intrusion,<lb n="574"/>Infect thy sap, and liue on thy confusion.<lb n="575" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>To mee shee speakes, shee moues mee for her<lb n="576"/>theame;<lb n="577"/>What, was I married to her in my dreame?<lb n="578"/>Or sleepe I now, and thinke I heare all this?<lb n="579"/>What error driues our eies and eares amisse?<lb n="580"/>Vntill I know this sure vncertaintie,<lb n="581"/>Ile entertaine the free'd fallacie.<lb n="582"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> goe bid the seruants spred for dinner.<lb n="583"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh for my beads, I crosse me for a sinner.<lb n="584"/>This is the Fairie land, oh spight of spights,<lb n="585"/>We talke with Goblins, Owles and Sprights;<lb n="586"/>If we obay them not, this will insue:<lb n="587"/>They'll sucke our breath, or pinch vs blacke and blew.<lb n="588" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Why prat'st thou to thy selfe, and answer'st not?<lb n="589"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> thou <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> thou snaile, thou slug, thou sot.<lb n="590"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I am transformed Master, am I not?<lb n="591"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I thinke thou art in minde, and so am I.<lb n="592"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay Master, both in minde, and in my shape.<lb n="593"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou hast thine owne forme.<lb n="594"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No, I am an Ape.<lb n="595"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>If thou art chang'd to ought, 'tis to an Asse.<lb n="596"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>'Tis true she rides me, and I long for grasse.<lb n="597"/>'Tis so, I am an Asse, else it could neuer be,<lb n="598"/>But I should know her as well as she knowes me.<lb n="599"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Come, come, no longer will I be a foole,<lb n="600"/>To put the finger in the eie and weepe;<lb n="601"/>Whil'st man and Master laughes my woes to scorne:<lb n="602"/>Come sir to dinner, <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> keepe the gate:<lb n="603"/>Husband Ile dine aboue with you to day,<lb n="604"/>And shriue you of a thousand idle prankes:<lb n="605"/>Sirra, if any aske you for your Master,<lb n="606"/>Say he dines forth, and let no creature enter:<lb n="607"/>Come sister, <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> play the Porter well.<lb n="608"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Am I in earth, in heauen, or in <seg type="homograph">hell</seg>?<lb n="609"/>Sleeping or waking, mad or well aduisde:<lb n="610"/>Knowne vnto these, and to my selfe disguisde:<lb n="611"/>Ile say as they say, and perseuer so:<lb n="612"/>And in this mist at all aduentures go.<lb n="613"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, shall I be Porter at the gate?<lb n="614"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, and let none enter, least I breake your pate.<lb n="615"/>
               </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Come, come, <hi rend="italic">Antipholus,</hi> we dine <seg type="homograph">to</seg> late.
      <pb n="H3v"/>
                        <lb n="616"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic">Actus Tertius. Scena Prima.</head>
            <lb n="617" rend="rj"/>
            <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus of Ephesus, his man Dromio, Angelo the<lb n="618"/>Goldsmith, and Balthaser the Merchant.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Good signior <hi rend="italic">Angelo</hi> you must excuse vs all,<lb n="620"/>My wife is shrewish when I keepe not howres;<lb n="621"/>Say that I lingerd with you at your shop<lb n="622"/>To see the making of her Carkanet,<lb n="623"/>And that to morrow you will bring it home.<lb n="624"/>But here's a villaine that would face me downe<lb n="625"/>He met me on the Mart, and that I beat him,<lb n="626"/>And charg'd him with a thousand markes in gold,<lb n="627"/>And that I did denie my wife and house;<lb n="628"/>Thou drunkard thou, what didst thou meane by this?<lb n="629" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Say what you wil sir, but I know what I know,<lb n="630" rend="rj"/>That you beat me at the Mart I haue your hand to show;<lb n="631" rend="rj"/>If <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythe"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>the</reg>
                  </choice> skin were parchment, &amp; <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythe"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>the</reg>
                  </choice> blows you gaue were ink,<lb n="632" rend="rj"/>Your owne hand-writing would tell you what I thinke.<lb n="633"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I thinke thou art an asse.<lb n="634"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry so it doth appeare<lb n="635"/>By the wrongs I suffer, and the blowes I beare,<lb n="636"/>I should kicke being kickt, and being at that passe,<lb n="637"/>You would keepe from my heeles, and beware of an asse.<lb n="638" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.An.</speaker>
              <ab>Y'are sad signior <hi rend="italic">Balthazar,</hi> pray God our cheer<lb n="639" rend="rj"/>May answer my good <seg type="homograph">will</seg>, and your good welcom here.<lb n="640" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Bal.</speaker>
              <ab>I hold your dainties cheap sir, &amp; your welcom deer.<lb n="641"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.An.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh signior <hi rend="italic">Balthazar,</hi> either at flesh or fish,<lb n="642"/>A table full of welcome, makes scarce one dainty dish.<lb n="643" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Bal.</speaker>
              <ab>Good meat sir is co[m]mon that euery churle affords.<lb n="644" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>And welcome more common, for thats nothing<lb n="645"/>but words.<lb n="646" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Bal.</speaker>
              <ab>Small cheere and great welcome, makes a mer-<lb n="647" type="inWord"/>rie feast.<lb n="648" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, to a niggardly Host, and more sparing guest:<lb n="649" rend="rj"/>But though my cates be meane, take them in good part,<lb n="650"/>Better cheere may you haue, but not with better hart.<lb n="651"/>But soft, my doore is lockt; goe bid them let vs in.<lb n="652"/>
               </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Maud, Briget, Marian, Cisley, Gillian, Ginn.</hi>
                  <lb n="653" rend="rj"/>
              </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Mome, Malthorse, Capon, Coxcombe, Idi-<lb type="inWord" n="654"/>ot, Patch,<lb n="655" rend="rj"/>Either get thee from the dore, or sit downe at the hatch:<lb n="656" rend="rj"/>Dost thou coniure for wenches, that <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythou"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>thou</reg>
                  </choice> calst for such store,<lb n="657" rend="rj"/>When one is one too many, goe get thee from the dore.<lb n="658" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>What patch is made our Porter? my Master<lb n="659"/>stayes in the street.<lb n="660" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Let him walke from whence he came, lest hee<lb n="661"/>catch cold on's feet.<lb n="662" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Who talks within there? hoa, open the dore.<lb n="663" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Right sir, Ile tell you when, and you'll tell<lb n="664"/>me wherefore.<lb n="665" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Wherefore? for my dinner: I haue not din'd to<lb n="666"/>day.<lb n="667" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nor to day here you must not come againe<lb n="668"/>when you may.<lb n="669" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>What art thou that keep'st mee out from the<lb n="670"/>howse I owe?<lb n="671" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>The Porter for this time Sir, and my name is<lb n="672"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Dromio.</hi>
                        <lb n="673" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>O villaine, thou hast stolne both mine office<lb n="674"/>and my name,<lb n="675"/>The one nere got me credit, the other mickle blame:<lb n="676"/>If thou hadst beene <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> to day in my place,<lb n="677" rend="rj"/>Thou wouldst haue chang'd thy face for a name, or thy<lb n="678"/>name for an asse.<lb n="679"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Luce.</stage>
                        <lb n="680" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>What a coile is there <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi>? who are those<lb n="681"/>at the gate?<lb n="682"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Let my Master in <hi rend="italic">Luce.</hi>
                        <lb n="683" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>Faith no, hee comes too late, and so tell your<lb n="684"/>Master.<lb n="685" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>O Lord I must laugh, haue at you with a Pro-<lb type="inWord" n="686"/>uerbe, 
                        <lb n="687"/>Shall I set in my staffe.<lb n="688" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>Haue at you with another, that's when? can<lb n="689"/>you tell?<lb n="690" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>If thy name be called <hi rend="italic">Luce, Luce</hi> thou hast an-swer'd<lb n="691"/>him well.<lb n="692" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Doe you heare you minion, you'll let vs in I<lb n="693"/>hope?<lb n="694"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>I thought to haue askt you.<lb n="695"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>And you said no.<lb n="696" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>So come helpe, well strooke, there was blow<lb n="697"/>for blow.<lb n="698"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou baggage let me in.<lb n="699"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>Can you tell for whose sake?<lb n="700"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Drom.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, knocke the doore hard.<lb n="701"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>Let him knocke till it ake.<lb n="702" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>You'll crie for this minion, if I beat the doore<lb n="703"/>downe.<lb n="704" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luce.</speaker>
              <ab>What needs all that, and a paire of stocks in the<lb n="705"/>towne?<lb n="706"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Adriana.</stage>
                        <lb n="707" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Who is that at the doore <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythat"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>that</reg>
                  </choice> keeps all this noise?<lb n="708" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>By my troth your towne is troubled with vn-<lb n="709" type="inWord"/>ruly boies.<lb n="710" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Are you there Wife? you might haue come<lb n="711"/>before.<lb n="712" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>Your wife sir knaue? go get you from the dore.<lb n="713" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>If you went in paine Master, this knaue wold<lb n="714"/>goe sore.<lb n="715" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Angelo.</speaker>
              <ab>Heere is neither cheere sir, nor welcome, we<lb n="716"/>would faine haue either.<lb n="717" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Baltz.</speaker>
              <ab>In debating which was best, wee shall part<lb n="718"/>with neither.<lb n="719" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>They stand at the doore, Master, bid them<lb n="720"/>welcome hither.<lb n="721" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>There is something in the winde, that we can-<lb n="722" type="inWord"/>not get in.<lb n="723" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>You would say so Master, if your garments<lb n="724"/>were thin.<lb n="725" rend="rj"/>Your cake here is warme within: you stand here in the<lb n="726"/>cold.<lb n="727" rend="rj"/>It would make a man mad as a Bucke to be so bought<lb n="728"/>and sold.<lb n="729" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Go fetch me something, Ile break ope the gate.<lb n="730" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Breake any breaking here, and Ile breake your<lb n="731"/>knaues pate.<lb n="732" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>A man may breake a word with your sir, and<lb n="733"/>words are but winde:<lb n="734"/>
                        <seg type="homograph">I</seg> and breake it in your face, so he break it not behinde.<lb n="735" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>It seemes thou want'st breaking, out vpon thee<lb n="736"/>hinde.<lb n="737" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Here's too much out vpon thee, I pray thee let<lb n="738"/>me in.<lb n="739" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, when fowles haue no feathers, and fish haue<lb n="740"/>no fin.<lb n="741"/>
               </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Well, Ile breake in: go borrow me a crow.<lb n="742" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>A crow without feather, Master meane you so;
      <pb n="H4"/>
                        <milestone unit="compo" n="C"/>
                        <lb n="743" rend="rj"/>For a fish without a finne, ther's a fowle without a fether,<lb n="744" rend="rj"/>If a crow help vs in sirra, wee'll plucke a crow together.<lb n="745"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Go, get thee gon, fetch me an iron Crow.<lb n="746"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Balth.</speaker>
              <ab>Haue patience sir, oh let it not be so,<lb n="747"/>Heerein you warre against your reputation,<lb n="748"/>And draw within the compasse of suspect<lb n="749"/>Th' vnuiolated  honor of your wife.<lb n="750"/>Once this your long experience of your wisedome,<lb n="751"/>Her sober vertue, yeares, and modestie,<lb n="752"/>Plead on your part some cause to you vnknowne;<lb n="753"/>And doubt not sir, but she will well excuse<lb n="754"/>Why at this time the dores are made against you.<lb n="755"/>Be rul'd by me, depart in patience,<lb n="756"/>And let vs to the Tyger all to dinner,<lb n="757"/>And about euening come your selfe alone,<lb n="758"/>To know the reason of this strange restraint:<lb n="759"/>If by strong hand you offer to breake in<lb n="760"/>Now in the stirring passage of the day,<lb n="761"/>A vulgar comment will be made of it;<lb n="762"/>And that supposed by the common rowt<lb n="763"/>Against your yet vngalled estimation,<lb n="764"/>That may with foule intrusion enter in,<lb n="765"/>And dwell vpon your graue when you are dead;<lb n="766"/>For slander liues vpon succession:<lb n="767"/>For euer hows'd, where it gets possession.<lb n="768"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>You haue preuail'd, I will depart in quiet,<lb n="769"/>And in despight of mirth meane to be merrie:<lb n="770"/>I know a wench of excellent discourse,<lb n="771"/>Prettie and wittie; wilde, and yet too gentle;<lb n="772"/>There will we dine: this woman that I meane<lb n="773"/>My wife (but I protest without desert)<lb n="774"/>Hath oftentimes vpbraided me withall:<lb n="775"/>To her will we to dinner, get you home<lb n="776"/>And fetch the chaine, by this I know 'tis made,<lb n="777"/>Bring it I pray you to the <hi rend="italic">Porpentine,</hi>
                        <lb n="778"/>For there's the house: That chaine will I bestow<lb n="779"/>(Be it for nothing but to spight my wife)<lb n="780"/>Vpon mine hostesse there, good sir make haste:<lb n="781"/>Since mine owne doores refuse to entertaine me,<lb n="782"/>Ile knocke else-where, to see if they'll disdaine me.<lb n="783"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ang.</speaker>
              <ab>Ile meet you at that place some houre hence.<lb n="784"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Do so, this iest shall cost me some expence.<lb n="785"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt.</stage>
                        <lb n="786"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Iuliana, with Antipholus of Siracusia.</stage>
                        <lb n="787"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Iulia.</speaker>
              <ab>And may it be that you haue quite forgot<lb n="788"/>A husbands office? shall <hi rend="italic">Antipholus</hi>
                        <lb n="789"/>Euen in the spring of Loue, thy Loue-springs rot?<lb n="790"/>Shall loue in buildings grow so ruinate?<lb n="791"/>If you did wed my sister for her wealth,<lb n="792" rend="rj"/>Then for her wealths-sake vse her with more kindnesse:<lb n="793"/>Or if you like else-where doe it by stealth,<lb n="794"/>Muffle your false loue with some shew of blindnesse:<lb n="795"/>Let not my sister read it in your eye:<lb n="796"/>Be not thy tongue thy owne shames Orator:<lb n="797"/>Looke sweet, speake faire, become disloyaltie:<lb n="798"/>Apparell vice like vertues harbenger:<lb n="799"/>Beare a faire presence, though your heart be tainted,<lb n="800"/>Teach sinne the carriage of a holy Saint,<lb n="801"/>Be secret false: what need she be acquainted?<lb n="802"/>What simple thiefe brags of his owne attaine?<lb n="803"/>'Tis double wrong to truant with your bed,<lb n="804"/>And let her read it in thy lookes at boord:<lb n="805"/>Shame hath a bastard fame, well managed,<lb n="806"/>
                        <seg type="homograph">Ill</seg> deeds is doubled with an euill word:<lb n="807"/>Alas poore women, make vs not beleeue<lb n="808"/>(Being compact of credit) that you loue vs,
      <milestone unit="compo" n="D"/>
                        <lb n="809"/>Though others haue the arme, shew vs the sleeue:<lb n="810"/>We in your motion turne, and you may moue vs.<lb n="811"/>Then gentle brother get you in againe;<lb n="812"/>Comfort my sister, cheere her, call her wise;<lb n="813"/>'Tis holy sport to be a little vaine,<lb n="814"/>When the sweet breath of flatterie conquers strife.<lb n="815" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Sweete Mistris, what your name is else I<lb n="816"/>know not;<lb n="817"/>Nor by what wonder you do hit of mine:<lb n="818" rend="rj"/>Lesse in your knowledge, and your grace you show not,<lb n="819"/>Then our earths wonder, more then earth diuine.<lb n="820"/>Teach me deere creature how to thinke and speake:<lb n="821"/>Lay open to my earthie grosse conceit:<lb n="822"/>Smothred in errors, feeble, shallow, weake,<lb n="823"/>The foulded meaning of your words deceit:<lb n="824"/>Against my soules pure truth, why labour you,<lb n="825"/>To make it wander in an vnknowne field?<lb n="826"/>Are you a god? would you create me new?<lb n="827"/>Transforme me then, and to your powre Ile yeeld.<lb n="828"/>But if that I am I, then well I know,<lb n="829"/>Your weeping sister is no wife of mine,<lb n="830"/>Nor to her bed no homage doe I owe:<lb n="831"/>Farre more, farre more, to you doe I decline:<lb n="832"/>Oh traine me not sweet Mermaide with thy note,<lb n="833"/>To drowne me in thy sister floud of teares:<lb n="834"/>Sing Siren for thy selfe, and I will dote:<lb n="835"/>Spread ore the siluer waues thy golden haires;<lb n="836"/>And as a bud Ile take thee, and there lie:<lb n="837"/>And in that glorious supposition thinke,<lb n="838"/>He gaines by death, that hath such meanes to die:<lb n="839"/>Let Loue, being light, be drowned if she sinke.<lb n="840"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>What are you mad, that you doe reason so?<lb n="841"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Not mad, but mated, how I doe not know.<lb n="842"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>It is a fault that springeth from your eie.<lb n="843" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>For gazing on your beames faire sun being by.<lb n="844" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Gaze when you should, and that will cleere<lb n="845"/>your sight.<lb n="846" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>As good to winke sweet loue, as looke on night.<lb n="847"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Why call you me loue? Call my sister so.<lb n="848"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thy sisters sister.<lb n="849"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>That's my sister.<lb n="850" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>No: it is thy selfe, mine owne selfes better part:<lb n="851"/>Mine eies cleere eie, my deere hearts deerer heart;<lb n="852"/>My foode, my fortune, and my sweet hopes aime;<lb n="853"/>My sole earths heauen, and my heauens claime.<lb n="854"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>All this my sister is, or else should be.<lb n="855"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Call thy selfe sister sweet, for I am thee:<lb n="856"/>Thee will I loue, and with thee lead my life;<lb n="857"/>Thou hast no husband yet, nor I no wife:<lb n="858"/>Giue me thy hand.<lb n="859"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh soft sir, hold you still:<lb n="860"/>Ile fetch my sister to get her good <seg type="homograph">will</seg>.  <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="861"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio, Siracusia.</stage>
                        <lb n="862" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Why how now <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> where run'st thou so<lb n="863"/>fast?<lb n="864" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Doe you know me sir? Am I <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi>? Am I<lb n="865"/>your man? Am I my selfe?<lb n="866" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou art <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> thou art my man, thou art<lb n="867"/>thy selfe.<lb n="868" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I am an asse, I am a womans man, and besides<lb n="869"/>my selfe.<lb n="870" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>What womans man? and how besides thy<lb n="871"/>selfe?<lb n="872" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marrie sir, besides my selfe, I am due to a woman:<lb n="873" rend="rj"/>One that claimes me, one that haunts me, one that will<lb n="874"/>haue me.
      <pb n="H4v"/>
                        <milestone unit="compo" n="B"/>
                        <lb n="875"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>What claime laies she to thee?<lb n="876" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry sir, such claime as you would lay to your<lb n="877" rend="rj"/>horse, and she would haue me as a beast, not that I bee-<lb n="878" rend="rj" type="inWord"/>ing a beast she would haue me, but that she being a ve-<lb n="879" type="inWord"/>rie beastly creature layes claime to me.<lb n="880"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>What is she?<lb n="881" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>A very reuerent body: <seg type="homograph">I</seg> such a one, as a man<lb n="882" rend="rj"/>may not speake of, without he say sir reuerence, I haue<lb n="883" rend="rj"/>but leane lucke in the match, and yet is she a wondrous<lb n="884"/>fat marriage.<lb n="885"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>How dost thou meane a fat marriage?<lb n="886" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry sir, she's the Kitchin wench, &amp; al grease,<lb n="887" rend="rj"/>and I know not what vse to put her <seg type="homograph">too</seg>, but to make a<lb n="888" rend="rj"/>Lampe of her, and run from her by her owne light. I<lb n="889" rend="rj"/>warrant, her ragges and the Tallow in them, will burne<lb n="890" rend="rj"/>a <hi rend="italic">Poland</hi> Winter: If she liues till doomesday, she'l burne<lb n="891"/>a weeke longer then the whole World.<lb n="892"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>What complexion is she of?<lb n="893" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Swart like my shoo, but her face nothing like<lb n="894" rend="rj"/>so cleane kept: for why? she sweats a man may goe o-uer-shooes<lb n="895"/>in the grime of it.<lb n="896"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>That's a fault that water will mend.<lb n="897" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No sir, 'tis in graine, <hi rend="italic">Noahs</hi> flood could not<lb n="898"/>do it.<lb n="899"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>What's her name?<lb n="900" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Nell</hi> Sir: but her name is three quarters, that's<lb n="901" rend="rj"/>an Ell and three quarters, will not measure her from hip<lb n="902"/>to hip.<lb n="903"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Then she beares some bredth?<lb n="904" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No longer from head to foot, then from hippe<lb n="905" rend="rj"/>to hippe: she is sphericall, like a globe: I could find out<lb n="906"/>Countries in her.<lb n="907"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>In what part of her body stands <hi rend="italic">Ireland</hi>?<lb n="908" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marry sir in her buttockes, I found it out by<lb n="909"/>the bogges.<lb n="910"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Where <hi rend="italic">Scotland</hi>?<lb n="911" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I found it by the barrennesse, hard in the palme<lb n="912"/>of the hand.<lb n="913"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Where <hi rend="italic">France</hi>?<lb n="914" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>In her forhead, arm'd and reuerted, making<lb n="915"/>warre against her heire.<lb n="916"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Where <hi rend="italic">England</hi>?<lb n="917" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I look'd for the chalkle Cliffes, but I could find<lb n="918" rend="rj"/>no whitenesse in them. But I guesse, it stood in her chin<lb n="919"/>by the salt rheume that ranne betweene <hi rend="italic">France,</hi> and it.<lb n="920"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Where <hi rend="italic">Spaine</hi>?<lb n="921" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Faith I saw it not: but I felt it hot in her breth.<lb n="922"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Where <hi rend="italic">America,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Indies</hi>?<lb n="923"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh sir, vpon her nose, all ore embellished with<lb n="924" rend="rj"/>Rubies, Carbuncles, Saphires, declining their rich As-<lb n="925" rend="rj" type="inWord"/>pect to the hot breath of Spaine, who sent whole Ar-<lb n="926" type="inWord"/>madoes of Carrects to be ballast at her nose.<lb n="927"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Where stood <hi rend="italic">Belgia,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Netherlands</hi>?<lb n="928" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh sir, I did not looke so low. To conclude,<lb n="929" rend="rj"/>this drudge or Diuiner layd claime to mee, call'd mee<lb n="930" rend="rj"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> swore I was assur'd to her, told me what priuie<lb n="931" rend="rj"/>markes I had about mee, as the marke of my shoulder,<lb n="932" rend="rj"/>the Mole in my necke, the great Wart on my left arme,<lb n="933" rend="rj"/>that I amaz'd ranne from her as a witch. And I thinke, if<lb n="934" rend="rj"/>my brest had not beene made of faith, and my heart of<lb n="935" rend="rj"/>steele, she had transform'd me to a Curtull dog, &amp; made<lb n="936"/>me turne i'th wheele.<lb n="937"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Go hie thee presently, post to the rode,<lb n="938"/>And if the winde blow any way from shore,<lb n="939"/>I will not harbour in this Towne to night.<lb n="940"/>If any Barke put forth, come to the Mart,<lb n="941"/>Where I will walke till thou returne to me:<lb n="942"/>If euerie one knowes vs, and we know none,<lb n="943"/>'Tis time I thinke to trudge, packe, and be gone.<lb n="944"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>As from a Beare a man would run for life,<lb n="945"/>So flie I from her that would be my wife.  <stage rend="italic">Exit</stage>
                        <lb n="946"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>There's none but Witches do inhabite heere,<lb n="947"/>And therefore 'tis hie time that I were hence:<lb n="948"/>She that doth call me husband, euen my soule<lb n="949"/>Doth for a wife abhorre. But her faire sister<lb n="950"/>Possest with such a gentle soueraigne grace,<lb n="951"/>Of such inchanting presence and discourse,<lb n="952"/>Hath almost made me Traitor to my selfe:<lb n="953"/>But least my selfe be guilty to selfe wrong,<lb n="954"/>Ile stop mine eares against the Mermaids song.<lb n="955"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Angelo with the Chaine.</stage>
                        <lb n="956"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ang.</speaker>
              <ab>Mr  <hi rend="italic">Antipholus.</hi>
                        <lb n="957"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg> that's my name.<lb n="958"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ang.</speaker>
              <ab>I know it well sir, loe here's the chaine,<lb n="959"/>I thought to haue tane you at the <hi rend="italic">Porpentine,</hi>
                        <lb n="960"/>The chaine vnfinish'd made me stay thus long.<lb n="961"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>What is your <seg type="homograph">will</seg> that I shal do with this?<lb n="962" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ang.</speaker>
              <ab>What please your selfe sir: I haue made it for<lb n="963"/>you.<lb n="964"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Made it for me sir, I bespoke it not.<lb n="965" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ang.</speaker>
              <ab>Not once, nor twice, but twentie times you<lb n="966"/>haue:<lb n="967"/>Go home with it, and please your Wife withall,<lb n="968"/>And soone at supper time Ile visit you,<lb n="969"/>And then receiue my money for the chaine.<lb n="970"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>I pray you sir receiue the money now.<lb n="971"/>For feare you ne're see chaine, nor mony more.<lb n="972"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ang.</speaker>
              <ab>You are a merry man sir, fare you well.  <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="973"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>What I should thinke of this, I cannot tell:<lb n="974"/>But this I thinke, there's no man is so vaine,<lb n="975"/>That would refuse so faire an offer'd Chaine.<lb n="976"/>I see a man heere needs not liue by shifts,<lb n="977"/>When in the streets he meetes such Golden gifts:<lb n="978"/>Ile to the Mart, and there for <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> stay,<lb n="979"/>If any ship put out, then straight away.  <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="980"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic">Actus Quartus. Scoena Prima.</head>
            <lb n="981"/>
            <stage rend="italic">Enter a Merchant, Goldsmith, and an Officer.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>You know since Pentecost the sum is due,<lb n="983"/>And since I haue not much importun'd you,<lb n="984"/>Nor now I had not, but that I am bound<lb n="985"/>To <hi rend="italic">Persia,</hi> and want Gilders for my voyage:<lb n="986"/>Therefore make present satisfaction,<lb n="987"/>Or Ile attach you by this Officer.<lb n="988"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Euen iust the sum that I do owe to you,<lb n="989"/>Is growing to me by <hi rend="italic">Antipholus,</hi>
                        <lb n="990"/>And in the instant that I met with you,<lb n="991"/>He had of me a Chaine, at fiue <seg type="homograph">a</seg> clocke<lb n="992"/>I shall receiue the money for the same:<lb n="993"/>Pleaseth you walke with me downe to his house,<lb n="994"/>I will discharge my bond, and thanke you too.<lb n="995"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus Ephes.<seg type="homograph">Dromio</seg> from the Courtizans.</stage>
                        <lb n="996" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offi.</speaker>
              <ab>That labour may you saue: See where he comes.<lb n="997" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>While I go to the Goldsmiths house, go thou
      <pb n="H5"/>
                        <lb n="998"/>And buy a ropes end, that will I bestow<lb n="999"/>Among my wife, and their confederates,<lb n="1000"/>For locking me out of my doores by day:<lb n="1001"/>But soft I see the Goldsmith; get thee gone,<lb n="1002"/>Buy thou a rope, and bring it home to me.<lb n="1003"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I buy a thousand pound a yeare, I buy a rope.<lb n="1004"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exit Dromio</stage>
                        <lb n="1005" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Eph.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>A man is well holpe vp that trusts to you,<lb n="1006"/>I promised your presence, and the Chaine,<lb n="1007"/>But neither Chaine nor Goldsmith came to me:<lb n="1008"/>Belike you thought our loue would last too long<lb n="1009"/>If it were chain'd together: and therefore came not.<lb n="1010"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Sauing your merrie humor: here's the note<lb n="1011" rend="rj"/>How much your Chaine weighs to the vtmost charect,<lb n="1012"/>The finenesse of the Gold, and chargefull fashion,<lb n="1013"/>Which doth amount to three odde Duckets more<lb n="1014"/>Then I stand debted to this Gentleman,<lb n="1015"/>I pray you see him presently discharg'd,<lb n="1016"/>For he is bound to Sea, and stayes but for it.<lb n="1017"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>I am not furnish'd with the present monie:<lb n="1018"/>Besides I haue some businesse in the towne,<lb n="1019"/>Good Signior take the stranger to my house,<lb n="1020"/>And with you take the Chaine, and bid my wife<lb n="1021"/>Disburse the summe, on the receit thereof,<lb n="1022"/>Perchance I will be there as soone as you.<lb n="1023" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Then you will bring the Chaine to her your<lb n="1024"/>selfe.<lb n="1025" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>No beare it with you, least I come not time e-<lb n="1026" type="inWord"/>nough. <lb n="1027" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Well sir, I will? Haue you the Chaine about<lb n="1028"/>you?<lb n="1029"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">And</seg> if I haue not sir, I hope you haue:<lb n="1030"/>Or else you may returne without your money.<lb n="1031" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay come I pray you sir, giue me the Chaine:<lb n="1032"/>Both winde and tide stayes for this Gentleman,<lb n="1033"/>And I <seg type="homograph">too</seg> blame haue held him heere too long.<lb n="1034" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Good Lord, you vse this dalliance to excuse<lb n="1035"/>Your breach of promise to the <hi rend="italic">Porpentine,</hi>
                        <lb n="1036"/>I should haue chid you for not bringing it,<lb n="1037"/>But like a shrew you first begin to brawle.<lb n="1038"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>The houre steales on, I pray you sir dispatch.<lb n="1039" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>You heare how he importunes me, the Chaine.<lb n="1040" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Why giue it to my wife, and fetch your mony.<lb n="1041" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Come, come, you know I gaue it you euen now.<lb n="1042"/>Either send the Chaine, or send me by some token.<lb n="1043"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Fie, now you run this humor out of breath,<lb n="1044"/>Come where's the Chaine, I pray you let me see it.<lb n="1045"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>My businesse cannot brooke this dalliance,<lb n="1046"/>Good sir say, <seg type="homograph">whe</seg>'r you'l answer me, or no:<lb n="1047"/>If not, Ile leaue him to the Officer.<lb n="1048"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I answer you? What should I answer you.<lb n="1049"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>The monie that you owe me for the Chaine.<lb n="1050"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I owe you none, till I receiue the Chaine.<lb n="1051"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>You know I gaue it you halfe an houre since.<lb n="1052" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>You gaue me none, you wrong mee much to<lb n="1053"/>say so.<lb n="1054"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>You wrong me more sir in denying it.<lb n="1055"/>Consider how it stands vpon my credit.<lb n="1056"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>Well Officer, arrest him at my suite.<lb n="1057" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offi.</speaker>
              <ab>I do, and charge you in the Dukes name to o-<lb n="1058" type="inWord"/>bey me.<lb n="1059"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>This touches me in reputation.<lb n="1060"/>Either consent to pay this sum for me,<lb n="1061"/>Or I attach you by this Officer.<lb n="1062"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Consent to pay thee that I neuer had:<lb n="1063"/>Arrest me foolish fellow if thou dar'st.<lb n="1064"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Heere is thy fee, arrest him Officer.<lb n="1065"/>I would not spare my brother in this case,<lb n="1066"/>If he should scorne me so apparantly.<lb n="1067"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offic.</speaker>
              <ab>I do arrest you sir, you heare the suite.<lb n="1068"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I do obey thee, till I giue thee baile.<lb n="1069"/>But sirrah, you shall buy this sport as deere,<lb n="1070"/>As all the mettall in your shop will answer.<lb n="1071"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Sir, sir, I shall haue Law in <hi rend="italic">Ephesus,</hi>
                        <lb n="1072"/>To your notorious shame, I doubt it not.<lb n="1073"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio Sira. from the Bay.</stage>
                        <lb n="1074"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, there's a Barke of <hi rend="italic">Epidamium,</hi>
                        <lb n="1075"/>That staies but till her Owner comes aboord,<lb n="1076"/>And then sir she beares away. Our fraughtage sir,<lb n="1077"/>I haue conuei'd aboord, and I haue bought<lb n="1078"/>The Oyle, the <hi rend="italic">Balsamum,</hi> and Aqua-vitae.<lb n="1079"/>The ship is in her trim, the merrie winde<lb n="1080"/>Blowes faire from land: they stay for nought at all,<lb n="1081"/>But for their Owner, Master, and your selfe.<lb n="1082" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>How now? a Madman? Why thou peeuish sheep<lb n="1083"/>What ship of <hi rend="italic">Epidamium</hi> staies for me.<lb n="1084"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>A ship you sent me <seg type="homograph">too</seg>, to hier waftage.<lb n="1085"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou drunken slaue, I sent thee for a rope,<lb n="1086"/>And told thee to what purpose, and what end.<lb n="1087"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>You sent me for a ropes end as soone,<lb n="1088"/>You sent me to the Bay sir, for a Barke.<lb n="1089"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I will debate this matter at more leisure<lb n="1090"/>And teach your eares to list me with more heede:<lb n="1091"/>To <hi rend="italic">Adriana</hi> Villaine hie thee straight:<lb n="1092"/>Giue her this key, and tell her in the Deske<lb n="1093"/>That's couer'd o're with Turkish Tapistrie,<lb n="1094"/>There is a purse of Duckets, let her send it:<lb n="1095"/>Tell her, I am arrested in the streete,<lb n="1096"/>And that shall baile me: hie thee slaue, be gone,<lb n="1097"/>On Officer to prison, till it come.  <stage rend="italic">Exeunt</stage>
                        <lb n="1098"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dromio.</speaker>
              <ab>To <hi rend="italic">Adriana,</hi> that is where we din'd,<lb n="1099"/>Where Dowsabell did claime me for her husband,<lb n="1100"/>She is too bigge I hope for me to compasse,<lb n="1101"/>Thither I must, although against my <seg type="homograph">will</seg>:<lb n="1102"/>For seruants must their Masters mindes fulfill.  <stage rend="italic">Exit</stage>
                        <lb n="1103"/>
                        <stage>
                     <hi rend="italic">Enter Adriana</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Luciana.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <lb n="1104"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Ah <hi rend="italic">Luciana,</hi> did he tempt thee so?<lb n="1105"/>Might'st thou perceiue austeerely in his eie,<lb n="1106"/>That he did plead in earnest, yea or no:<lb n="1107"/>Look'd he or red or pale, or sad or merrily?<lb n="1108"/>What obseruation mad'st thou in this case?<lb n="1109"/>Oh, his hearts Meteors tilting in his face.<lb n="1110"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>First he deni'de you had in him no right.<lb n="1111" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>He meant he did me none: the more my spight<lb n="1112"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Then swore he that he was a stranger heere.<lb n="1113" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>And true he swore, though yet forsworne hee<lb n="1114"/>were.<lb n="1115"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Then pleaded I for you.<lb n="1116"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>And what said he?<lb n="1117"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>That loue I begg'd for you, he begg'd of me.<lb n="1118" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>With what perswasion did he tempt thy loue?<lb n="1119" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>With words, that in an honest suit might moue.<lb n="1120"/>First, he did praise my beautie, then my speech.<lb n="1121"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Did'st speake him faire?<lb n="1122"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Haue patience I beseech.<lb n="1123"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I cannot, nor I will not hold me still.<lb n="1124"/>My tongue, though not my heart, shall haue his <seg type="homograph">will</seg>.<lb n="1125"/>He is deformed, crooked, old, and sere,<lb n="1126"/>Ill-fac'd, worse bodied, shapelesse euery where:<lb n="1127"/>Vicious, vngentle, foolish, blunt, vnkinde,
      <pb n="H5v"/>
                        <milestone unit="compo" n="D"/>
                        <lb n="1128"/>Stigmaticall in making worse in minde.<lb n="1129"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Who would be iealous then of such a one?<lb n="1130"/>No euill lost is wail'd, when it is gone.<lb n="1131"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Ah but I thinke him better then I say:<lb n="1132"/>And yet would herein others eies were worse:<lb n="1133"/>Farre from her nest the Lapwing cries away;<lb n="1134"/>My heart praies for him, though my tongue doe curse.<lb n="1135"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter S.Dromio.</stage>
                        <lb n="1136" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Here goe: the deske, the purse, sweet now make<lb n="1137"/>haste.<lb n="1138"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>How hast thou lost thy breath?<lb n="1139"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>By running fast.<lb n="1140"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Where is thy Master <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi>? Is he well?<lb n="1141"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No, he's in Tartar limbo, worse then <seg type="homograph">hell</seg>:<lb n="1142"/>A diuell in an euerlasting garment hath him;<lb n="1143"/>On whose hard heart is button'd vp with steele:<lb n="1144"/>A Feind, a Fairie, pittilesse and ruffe:<lb n="1145"/>A Wolfe, nay worse, a fellow all in buffe:<lb n="1146" rend="rj"/>A back friend, a shoulder-clapper, one that counterma[n]ds<lb n="1147"/>The passages of allies, creekes, and narrow lands:<lb n="1148"/>A hound that runs Counter, and yet draws drifoot well,<lb n="1149" rend="rj"/>One that before the Iudgme[n]t carries poore soules to <seg type="homograph">hel</seg>.<lb n="1150"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Why man, what is the matter?<lb n="1151" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I doe not know the matter, hee is rested on<lb n="1152"/>the case.<lb n="1153"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>What is he arrested? tell me at whose suite?<lb n="1154" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I know not at whose suite he is arested well;<lb n="1155" rend="rj"/>but is in a suite of buffe which rested him, that can I tell,<lb n="1156" rend="rj"/>will you send him Mistris redemption, the monie in<lb n="1157"/>his deske.<lb n="1158"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Go fetch it Sister: this I wonder at.<lb n="1159"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exit Luciana.</stage>
                        <lb n="1160"/>Thus he vnknowne to me should be in debt:<lb n="1161"/>Tell me, was he arested on a band?<lb n="1162"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Not on a band, but on a stronger thing:<lb n="1163"/>A chaine, a chaine, doe you not <seg type="homograph">here</seg> it ring.<lb n="1164"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adria.</speaker>
              <ab>What, the chaine?<lb n="1165"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No, no, the bell, 'tis time that I were gone:<lb n="1166" rend="rj"/>It was two ere I left him, and now the clocke strikes one.<lb n="1167"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>The houres come backe, that did I neuer <seg type="homograph">here</seg>.<lb n="1168" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh yes, if any houre meete a Serieant, <seg type="homograph">a</seg> turnes<lb n="1169"/>backe for verie feare.<lb n="1170" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>As if time were in debt: how fondly do'st thou<lb n="1171"/>reason?<lb n="1172" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Time is a verie bankerout, and owes more then<lb n="1173"/>he's worth to season.<lb n="1174"/>Nay, he's a theefe too: haue you not heard men say,<lb n="1175"/>That time comes stealing on by night and day?<lb n="1176"/>If I be in debt and theft, and a Serieant in the way,<lb n="1177"/>Hath he not reason to turne backe an houre in a day?<lb n="1178"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Luciana.</stage>
                        <lb n="1179" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Go <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> there's the monie, beare it straight,<lb n="1180"/>And bring thy Master home imediately.<lb n="1181"/>Come sister, I am prest downe with conceit:<lb n="1182"/>Conceit, my comfort and my iniurie.  <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="1183"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus Siracusia.</stage>
                        <lb n="1184"/>There's not a man I meete but doth salute me<lb n="1185"/>As if I were their well acquainted friend,<lb n="1186"/>And euerie one doth call me by my name:<lb n="1187"/>Some tender monie to me, some inuite me;<lb n="1188"/>Some other giue me thankes for kindnesses;<lb n="1189"/>Some offer me Commodities to buy.<lb n="1190"/>Euen now a tailor cal'd me in his shop,<lb n="1191"/>And show'd me Silkes that he had bought for me,<lb n="1192"/>And therewithall tooke measure of my body.<lb n="1193"/>Sure these are but imaginarie wiles,<lb n="1194"/>And lapland Sorcerers inhabite here.<lb n="1195"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio. <seg type="homograph">Sir</seg>.</stage>
                        <lb n="1196" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, here's the gold you sent me for: what<lb n="1197"/>haue you got the picture of old <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi> new apparel'd?<lb n="1198" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>What gold is this? What <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi> do'st thou<lb n="1199"/>meane?<lb n="1200" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Not that <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi> that kept the Paradise: but<lb n="1201" rend="rj"/>that <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi> that keepes the prison; hee that goes in the<lb n="1202" rend="rj"/>calues-skin, that was kil'd for the Prodigall: hee that<lb n="1203" rend="rj"/>came behinde you sir, like an euill angel, and bid you for-<lb n="1204" type="inWord"/>sake your libertie.<lb n="1205"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I vnderstand thee not.<lb n="1206" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No? why 'tis a plaine case: he that went like<lb n="1207" rend="rj"/>a Base-Viole in a case of leather; the man sir, that when<lb n="1208" rend="rj"/>gentlemen are tired giues them a sob, and rests them:<lb n="1209" rend="rj"/>he sir, that takes pittie on decaied men, and giues them<lb n="1210" rend="rj"/>suites of durance: he that sets vp his rest to doe more ex-<lb n="1211" type="inWord"/>ploits with his Mace, then a Moris Pike.<lb n="1212"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>What thou mean'st an officer?<lb n="1213" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg> sir, the Serieant of the Band: he that brings<lb n="1214" rend="rj"/>any man to answer it that breakes his Band: one that<lb n="1215" rend="rj"/>thinkes a man alwaies going to bed, and saies, God giue<lb n="1216"/>you good rest.<lb n="1217"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Well sir, there rest in your foolerie:<lb n="1218" rend="rj"/>Is there any ships puts forth to night? may we be gone?<lb n="1219" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Why sir, I brought you word an houre since,<lb n="1220" rend="rj"/>that the Barke <hi rend="italic">Expedition</hi> put forth to night, and then<lb n="1221" rend="rj"/>were you hindred by the Serieant to tarry for the <hi rend="italic">Hoy</hi>
                        <lb n="1222" rend="rj"/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Delay:</hi> Here are the angels that you sent for to deliuer<lb n="1223"/>you.<lb n="1224"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>The fellow is distract, and so am I,<lb n="1225"/>And here we wander in illusions:<lb n="1226"/>Some blessed power deliuer vs from hence.<lb n="1227"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter a Curtizan.</stage>
                        <lb n="1228"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>Well met, well met, Master <hi rend="italic">Antipholus:</hi>
                        <lb n="1229"/>I see sir you haue found the Gold-smith now:<lb n="1230"/>Is that the chaine you promis'd me to day.<lb n="1231"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Sathan auoide, I charge thee tempt me not.<lb n="1232"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, is this Mistris <hi rend="italic">Sathan</hi>?<lb n="1233"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>It is the diuell.<lb n="1234"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay, she is worse, she is the diuels dam:
      <milestone unit="compo" n="C"/>
                        <lb n="1235" rend="rj"/>And here she comes in the habit of a light wench, and<lb n="1236" rend="rj"/>thereof comes, that the wenches say God dam me, That's<lb n="1237" rend="rj"/>as much to say, God make me a light wench: It is writ-<lb type="inWord" n="1238" rend="rj"/>ten, they appeare to men like angels of light, light is an<lb n="1239" rend="rj"/>effect of fire, and fire will burne: <hi rend="italic">ergo,</hi> light wenches will<lb n="1240"/>burne, come not neere her.<lb n="1241"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>Your man and you are maruailous merrie sir.<lb n="1242"/>Will you goe with me, wee'll mend our dinner here?<lb n="1243" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, if do expect spoon-meate, or bespeake<lb n="1244"/>a long spoone.<lb n="1245"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Why <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi>?<lb n="1246" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Marrie he must haue a long spoone that must<lb n="1247"/>eate with the diuell.<lb n="1248" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Auoid then fiend, what tel'st thou me of sup-<seg type="carryOver">ping?</seg>
                        <lb n="1249"/>Thou art, as you are all a sorceresse:<lb n="1250"/>I coniure thee to leaue me, and be gon.<lb n="1251"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>Giue me the ring of mine you had at dinner,<lb n="1252"/>Or for my Diamond the Chaine you promis'd,<lb n="1253"/>And Ile be gone sir, and not trouble you.<lb n="1254" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Some diuels aske but the parings of ones naile,
      <pb n="H6"/>
                        <milestone unit="compo" n="B"/>
                        <lb n="1255" rend="rj"/>a rush, a haire, a drop of blood, a pin, a nut, a  cherrie-<lb n="1256" rend="rj" type="inWord"/>stone: but she more couetous, wold haue a chaine: Ma-<lb n="1257" rend="rj" type="inWord"/>ster be wise, <seg type="homograph">and</seg> if you giue it her, the diuell will shake<lb n="1258"/>her Chaine, and fright vs with it.<lb n="1259"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>I pray you sir my Ring, or else the Chaine,<lb n="1260"/>I hope you do not meane to cheate me so?<lb n="1261"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Auant thou witch: Come <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> let vs go.<lb n="1262" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Flie pride saies the Pea-cocke, Mistris that<lb n="1263"/>you know.  <stage rend="italic">Exit.</stage>
                        <lb n="1264"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>Now out of doubt <hi rend="italic">Antipholus</hi> is mad,<lb n="1265"/>Else would he neuer so demeane himselfe,<lb n="1266"/>A Ring he hath of mine worth fortie Duckets,<lb n="1267"/>And for the same he promis'd me a Chaine,<lb n="1268"/>Both one and other he denies me now:<lb n="1269"/>The reason that I gather he is mad,<lb n="1270"/>Besides this present instance of his rage,<lb n="1271"/>Is a mad tale he told to day at dinner,<lb n="1272"/>Of his owne doores being shut against his entrance.<lb n="1273"/>Belike his wife acquainted with his fits,<lb n="1274"/>On purpose shut the doores against his way:<lb n="1275"/>My way is now to hie home to his house,<lb n="1276"/>And tell his wife, that being Lunaticke,<lb n="1277"/>He rush'd into my house, and tooke perforce<lb n="1278"/>My Ring away. This course I fittest choose,<lb n="1279"/>For fortie Duckets is too much to loose.<lb n="1280"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus Ephes. with a Iailor.</stage>
                        <lb n="1281"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">An.</speaker>
              <ab>Feare me not man, I will not breake away,<lb n="1282"/>Ile giue thee ere I leaue thee so much money<lb n="1283"/>To warrant thee as I am rested for.<lb n="1284"/>My wife is in a wayward moode to day,<lb n="1285"/>And will not lightly trust the Messenger,<lb n="1286"/>That I should be attach'd in <hi rend="italic">Ephesus,</hi>
                        <lb n="1287"/>I tell you 'twill sound harshly in her eares.<lb n="1288"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Dromio Eph. with a ropes end.</stage>
                        <lb n="1289"/>Heere comes my Man, I thinke he brings the monie.<lb n="1290"/>How now sir? Haue you that I sent you for?<lb n="1291"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Here's that I warrant you will pay them all.<lb n="1292"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>But where's the Money?<lb n="1293"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Why sir, I gaue the Monie for the Rope.<lb n="1294"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Fiue hundred Duckets villaine for a rope?<lb n="1295"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Ile serue you sir fiue hundred at the rate.<lb n="1296"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>To what end did I bid thee hie thee home?<lb n="1297" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>To a ropes end sir, and to that end am I re-turn'd.<lb n="1298"/>
                        <lb n="1299"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>And to that end sir, I will welcome you.<lb n="1300"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offi.</speaker>
              <ab>Good sir be patient.<lb n="1301" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay 'tis for me to be patient, I am in aduer-<lb n="1302" type="inWord"/>sitie. <lb n="1303"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offi.</speaker>
              <ab>Good now hold thy tongue.<lb n="1304" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay, rather perswade him to hold his hands.<lb n="1305"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou whoreson senselesse Villaine.<lb n="1306" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I would I were senselesse sir, that I might<lb n="1307"/>not feele your blowes.<lb n="1308" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou art sensible in nothing but blowes, and<lb n="1309"/>so is an Asse.<lb n="1310" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I am an Asse indeede, you may prooue it by<lb n="1311" rend="rj"/>my long eares. I haue serued him from the houre of my<lb n="1312" rend="rj"/>Natiuitie to this instant, and haue nothing at his hands<lb n="1313" rend="rj"/>for my seruice but blowes. When I am cold, he heates<lb n="1314" rend="rj"/>me with beating: when I am warme, he cooles me with<lb n="1315" rend="rj"/>beating: I am wak'd with it when I sleepe, rais'd with<lb n="1316" rend="rj"/>it when I sit, driuen out of doores with it when I goe<lb n="1317" rend="rj"/>from home, welcom'd home with it when I returne, nay<lb n="1318" rend="rj"/>I beare it on my shoulders, as a begger woont her brat:<lb n="1319" rend="rj"/>and I thinke when he hath lam'd me, I shall begge with<lb n="1320"/>it from doore to doore.<lb n="1321"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Adriana, Luciana, Courtizan, and a Schoole-<lb type="inWord" n="1322"/>master, call'd Pinch.</stage>
                        <lb n="1323" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Come goe along, my wife is comming yon-<lb n="1324" type="inWord"/>der. <lb n="1325" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Mistris <hi rend="italic">respice finem,</hi> respect your end, or ra-<lb n="1326" rend="rj" type="inWord"/>ther the prophesie like the Parrat, beware the ropes end.<lb n="1327"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Wilt thou still talke?  <stage rend="italic">Beats Dro.</stage>
                        <lb n="1328" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Curt.</speaker>
              <ab>How say you now? Is not your husband mad?<lb n="1329"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>His inciuility confirmes no lesse:<lb n="1330"/>Good Doctor <hi rend="italic">Pinch,</hi> you are a Coniurer,<lb n="1331"/>Establish him in his true sence againe,<lb n="1332"/>And I will please you what you will demand.<lb n="1333"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Alas how fiery, and how sharpe he lookes.<lb n="1334"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>Marke, how he trembles in his extasie.<lb n="1335" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Pinch.</speaker>
              <ab>Giue me your hand, and let mee feele your<lb n="1336"/>pulse.<lb n="1337"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>There is my hand, and let it feele your eare.<lb n="1338" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Pinch.</speaker>
              <ab>I charge thee Sathan, hous'd within this man,<lb n="1339"/>To yeeld possession to my holie praiers,<lb n="1340"/>And to thy state of darknesse hie thee straight,<lb n="1341"/>I coniure thee by all the Saints in heauen.<lb n="1342"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Peace doting wizard, peace; I am not mad.<lb n="1343" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh that thou wer't not, poore distressed soule.<lb n="1344" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>You Minion you, are these your Customers?<lb n="1345"/>Did this Companion with the saffron face<lb n="1346"/>Reuell and feast it at my house to day,<lb n="1347"/>Whil'st vpon me the guiltie doores were shut,<lb n="1348"/>And I denied to enter in my house.<lb n="1349" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>O husband, God doth know you din'd at home<lb n="1350"/>Where would you had remain'd vntill this time,<lb n="1351"/>Free from these slanders, and this open shame.<lb n="1352" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Din'd at home? Thou Villaine, what sayest<lb n="1353"/>thou?<lb n="1354"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Sir sooth to say, you did not dine at home.<lb n="1355" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Were not my doores lockt vp, and I shut out?<lb n="1356" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Perdie, your doores were lockt, and you shut<lb n="1357"/>out.<lb n="1358"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>And did not she her selfe reuile me there?<lb n="1359"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Sans</hi> Fable, she her selfe reuil'd you there.<lb n="1360" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Did not her Kitchen maide raile, taunt, and<lb n="1361"/>scorne me?<lb n="1362"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Certis</hi> she did, the kitchin vestall scorn'd you.<lb n="1363"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>And did not I in rage depart from thence?<lb n="1364" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>In veritie you did, my bones beares witnesse,<lb n="1365"/>That since haue felt the vigor of his rage.<lb n="1366"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Is't good to sooth him in these contraries?<lb n="1367"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Pinch.</speaker>
              <ab>It is no shame, the fellow finds his vaine,<lb n="1368"/>And yeelding to him, humors well his frensie.<lb n="1369" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou hast subborn'd the Goldsmith to arrest<lb n="1370"/>mee.<lb n="1371"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Alas, I sent you Monie to redeeme you,<lb n="1372"/>By <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> heere, who came in <seg type="homograph">hast</seg> for it.<lb n="1373" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Monie by me? Heart and good <seg type="homograph">will</seg> you might,<lb n="1374"/>But surely Master not a ragge of Monie.<lb n="1375" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Wentst not thou to her for a purse of Duckets.<lb n="1376"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>He came to me, and I deliuer'd it.<lb n="1377"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luci.</speaker>
              <ab>And I am witnesse with her that she did:<lb n="1378"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>God and the Rope-maker beare me witnesse,<lb n="1379"/>That I was sent for nothing but a rope.<lb n="1380"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Pinch.</speaker>
              <ab>Mistris, both Man and Master is possest,<lb n="1381"/>I know it by their pale and deadly lookes,
      <pb n="H6v"/>
                        <lb n="1382"/>They must be bound and laide in some darke roome.<lb n="1383" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Say wherefore didst thou  locke me forth to day,<lb n="1384"/>And why dost thou denie the bagge of gold?<lb n="1385"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I did not gentle husband locke thee forth.<lb n="1386"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>And gentle Mr I receiu'd no gold:<lb n="1387"/>But I confesse sir, that we were lock'd out.<lb n="1388" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Dissembling Villain, thou speak'st false in both<lb n="1389"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Dissembling harlot, thou art false in all,<lb n="1390"/>And art confederate with a damned packe,<lb n="1391"/>To make a loathsome abiect scorne of me:<lb n="1392"/>But with these nailes, Ile plucke out these false eyes,<lb n="1393"/>That would behold in me this shamefull sport.<lb n="1394"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter three or foure, and offer to binde him:<lb n="1395"/>Hee striues.</stage>
                        <lb n="1396" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh binde him, binde him, let him not come<lb n="1397"/>neere me.<lb n="1398" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Pinch.</speaker>
              <ab>More company, the fiend is strong within him<lb n="1399" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Aye me poore man, how pale and wan he looks.<lb n="1400" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>What will you murther me, thou Iailor thou?<lb n="1401" rend="rj"/>I am thy prisoner, wilt thou suffer them to make a res-<lb n="1402" type="inWord"/>cue? <lb n="1403" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offi.</speaker>
              <ab>Masters let him go: he is my prisoner, and you<lb n="1404"/>shall not haue him.<lb n="1405"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Pinch.</speaker>
              <ab>Go binde this man, for he is franticke too.<lb n="1406"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>What wilt thou do, thou peeuish Officer?<lb n="1407"/>Hast thou delight to see a wretched man<lb n="1408"/>Do outrage and displeasure to himselfe?<lb n="1409"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Offi.</speaker>
              <ab>He is my prisoner, if I let him go,<lb n="1410"/>The debt he owes will be requir'd of me.<lb n="1411"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I will discharge thee ere I go from thee,<lb n="1412"/>Beare me forthwith vnto his Creditor,<lb n="1413"/>And knowing how the debt growes I will pay it.<lb n="1414"/>Good Master Doctor see him safe conuey'd<lb n="1415"/>Home to my house, oh most vnhappy day.<lb n="1416"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh most vnhappie strumpet.<lb n="1417"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Master, I am heere entred in bond for you.<lb n="1418" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Out on thee Villaine, wherefore dost thou mad<lb n="1419"/>mee?<lb n="1420" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Will you be bound for nothing, be mad good<lb n="1421"/>Master, cry the diuell.<lb n="1422" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>God helpe poore soules, how idlely doe they<lb n="1423"/>talke.<lb n="1424"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Go beare him hence, sister go you with me:<lb n="1425"/>Say now, whose suite is he arrested at?<lb n="1426"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt. Manet Offic. Adri. Luci. Courtizan</stage>
                        <lb n="1427"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Off.</speaker>
              <ab>One <hi rend="italic">Angelo</hi> a Goldsmith, do you know him?<lb n="1428" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I know the man: what is the summe he owes?<lb n="1429"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Off.</speaker>
              <ab>Two hundred Duckets.<lb n="1430"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Say, how growes it due.<lb n="1431"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Off.</speaker>
              <ab>Due for a Chaine your husband had of him.<lb n="1432" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>He did bespeake a Chain for me, but had it not.<lb n="1433"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>When as your husband all in rage to day<lb n="1434"/>Came to my house, and tooke away my Ring,<lb n="1435"/>The Ring I saw vpon his finger now,<lb n="1436"/>Straight after did I meete him with a Chaine.<lb n="1437"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>It may be so, but I did neuer see it.<lb n="1438"/>Come Iailor, bring me where the Goldsmith is,<lb n="1439"/>I long to know the truth heereof at large.<lb n="1440"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus Siracusia with his Rapier drawne,<lb n="1441"/>and Dromio Sirac.</stage>
                        <lb n="1442"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>God for thy mercy, they are loose againe.<lb n="1443"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>And come with naked swords,<lb n="1444"/>Let's call more helpe to haue them bound againe.<lb n="1445"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Runne all out.</stage>
                        <lb n="1446"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Off.</speaker>
              <ab>Away, they'l kill vs.<lb n="1447"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt omnes, as fast as may be, frighted.</stage>
                        <lb n="1448"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I see these Witches are affraid of swords.<lb n="1449" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>She that would be your wife, now ran from<lb n="1450"/>you.<lb n="1451" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Come to the Centaur, fetch our stuffe from<lb n="1452"/>thence:<lb n="1453"/>I long that we were safe and sound aboord.<lb n="1454" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Faith stay heere this night, they will surely do<lb n="1455" rend="rj"/>vs no harme: you saw they speake vs faire, giue vs gold:<lb n="1456" rend="rj"/>me thinkes they are such a gentle Nation, that but for<lb n="1457" rend="rj"/>the Mountaine of mad flesh that claimes mariage of me,<lb n="1458" rend="rj"/>I could finde in my heart to stay heere still, and turne<lb n="1459"/>Witch.<lb n="1460"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I will not stay to night for all the Towne,<lb n="1461"/>Therefore away, to get our stuffe aboord. <stage rend="italic">Exeunt</stage>
                        <lb n="1462"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head rend="italic">Actus Quintus. Scoena Prima.</head>
            <lb n="1463"/>
            <stage rend="italic">Enter the Merchant and the Goldsmith.</stage>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>I am sorry Sir that I haue hindred you,<lb n="1465"/>But I protest he had the Chaine of me,<lb n="1466"/>Though most dishonestly he doth denie it.<lb n="1467"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>How is the man esteem'd heere in the Citie?<lb n="1468"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Of very reuerent reputation sir,<lb n="1469"/>Of credit infinite, highly belou'd,<lb n="1470"/>Second to none that liues heere in the Citie:<lb n="1471"/>His word might beare my wealth at any time.<lb n="1472" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>Speake  softly, yonder as I thinke he walkes.<lb n="1473"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus and Dromio againe.</stage>
                        <lb n="1474" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>'Tis so: and that selfe chaine about his necke,<lb n="1475"/>Which he forswore most monstrously to haue.<lb n="1476"/>Good sir draw neere to me, Ile speake to him:<lb n="1477"/>Signior <hi rend="italic">Antipholus,</hi> I wonder much<lb n="1478"/>That you would put me to this shame and trouble,<lb n="1479"/>And not without some scandall to your selfe,<lb n="1480"/>With circumstance and oaths, so to denie<lb n="1481"/>This Chaine, which now you weare so openly.<lb n="1482"/>Beside the charge, the shame, imprisonment,<lb n="1483"/>You haue done wrong to this my honest friend,<lb n="1484"/>Who but for staying on our Controuersie,<lb n="1485"/>Had hoisted saile, and put to sea to day:<lb n="1486"/>This Chaine you had of me, can you deny it?<lb n="1487"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I thinke I had, I neuer did deny it.<lb n="1488"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>Yes that you did sir, and forswore it too.<lb n="1489"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Who heard me to denie it or forsweare it?<lb n="1490" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>These eares of mine thou knowst did hear thee:<lb n="1491"/>Fie on thee wretch, 'tis pitty that thou liu'st<lb n="1492"/>To walke where any honest men resort.<lb n="1493"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Thou art a Villaine to impeach me thus,<lb n="1494"/>Ile proue mine honor, and mine honestie<lb n="1495"/>Against thee presently, if thou dar'st stand:<lb n="1496"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>I dare and do defie thee for a villaine.<lb n="1497" rend="rj"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">They draw. Enter Adriana, Luciana, Courtezan, &amp; others.</stage>
                        <lb n="1498"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Hold, hurt him not for God sake, he is mad,<lb n="1499"/>Some get within him, take his sword away:<lb n="1500"/>Binde <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> too, and beare them to my house.<lb n="1501" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Runne master run, for Gods sake take a house,<lb n="1502"/>This is some Priorie, in, or we are spoyl'd.<lb n="1503"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt to the Priorie.</stage>
                        <pb n="I1"/>
                        <lb n="1504"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Ladie Abbesse.</stage>
                        <lb n="1505"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>Be quiet people, wherefore throng you hither?<lb n="1506"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>To fetch my poore distracted husband hence,<lb n="1507"/>Let vs come in, that we may binde him fast,<lb n="1508"/>And beare him home for his recouerie.<lb n="1509"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>I knew he was not in his perfect wits.<lb n="1510"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>I am sorry now that I did draw on him.<lb n="1511"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>How long hath this possession held the man.<lb n="1512"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>This weeke he hath beene heauie, sower sad,<lb n="1513"/>And much different from the man he was:<lb n="1514"/>But till this afternoone his passion<lb n="1515"/>Ne're brake into extremity of rage.<lb n="1516" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>Hath he not lost much wealth by wrack of sea,<lb n="1517"/>Buried some deere friend, hath not else his eye<lb n="1518"/>Stray'd his affection in vnlawfull loue,<lb n="1519"/>A sinne preuailing much in youthfull men,<lb n="1520"/>Who giue their eies the liberty of gazing.<lb n="1521"/>Which of these sorrowes is he subiect <seg type="homograph">too</seg>?<lb n="1522"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>To none of these, except it be the last,<lb n="1523"/>Namely, some loue that drew him oft from home.<lb n="1524"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>You should for that haue reprehended him.<lb n="1525"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Why so I did.<lb n="1526"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg> but not rough enough.<lb n="1527"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>As roughly as my modestie would let me.<lb n="1528"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>Haply in priuate.<lb n="1529"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>And in assemblies too.<lb n="1530"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg>, but not enough.<lb n="1531"/>
               </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>It was the copie of our Conference.<lb n="1532"/>In bed he slept not for my vrging it,<lb n="1533"/>At boord he fed not for my vrging it:<lb n="1534"/>Alone, it was the subiect of my Theame:<lb n="1535"/>In company I often glanced it:<lb n="1536"/>Still did I tell him, it was vilde and bad.<lb n="1537"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>And thereof came it, that the man was mad.<lb n="1538"/>The venome clamors of a iealous woman,<lb n="1539"/>Poisons more deadly then a mad dogges tooth.<lb n="1540"/>It seemes his sleepes were hindred by thy railing,<lb n="1541"/>And thereof comes it that his head is light.<lb n="1542"/>Thou saist his meate was sawc'd with thy vpbraidings,<lb n="1543"/>Vnquiet meales make <seg type="homograph">ill</seg> digestions,<lb n="1544"/>Thereof the raging fire of feauer bred,<lb n="1545"/>And what's a Feauer, but a fit of madnesse?<lb n="1546"/>Thou sayest his sports were hindred by thy bralles.<lb n="1547"/>Sweet recreation barr'd, what doth ensue<lb n="1548"/>But moodie and dull melancholly,<lb n="1549"/>Kinsman to grim and comfortlesse dispaire,<lb n="1550"/>And at her heeles a huge infectious troope<lb n="1551"/>Of  pale distemperatures, and foes to life?<lb n="1552"/>In food, in sport, and life-preseruing rest<lb n="1553"/>To be disturb'd, would mad or man, or beast:<lb n="1554"/>The consequence is then, thy iealous fits<lb n="1555"/>Hath scar'd thy husband from the vse of wits.<lb n="1556"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>She neuer reprehended him but mildely,<lb n="1557"/>When he demean'd himselfe, rough, rude, and wildly,<lb n="1558"/>Why beare you these rebukes, and answer not?<lb n="1559"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adri.</speaker>
              <ab>She did betray me to my owne reproofe,<lb n="1560"/>Good people enter, and lay hold on him.<lb n="1561"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>No, not a creature enters in my house.<lb n="1562" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ad.</speaker>
              <ab>Then let your seruants bring my husband forth<lb n="1563"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>Neither: he tooke this place for sanctuary,<lb n="1564"/>And it shall priuiledge him from your hands,<lb n="1565"/>Till I haue brought him to his wits againe,<lb n="1566"/>Or loose my labour in assaying it.<lb n="1567"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I will attend my husband, be his nurse,<lb n="1568"/>Diet his sicknesse, for it is my Office,<lb n="1569"/>And will haue no atturney but my selfe,<lb n="1570"/>And therefore let me haue him home with me.<lb n="1571"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>Be patient, for I will not let him stirre,<lb n="1572"/>Till I haue vs'd the approoued meanes I haue,<lb n="1573"/>With wholsome sirrups, drugges, and holy prayers<lb n="1574"/>To make of him a formall man againe:<lb n="1575"/>It is a branch and parcell of mine oath,<lb n="1576"/>A charitable dutie of my order,<lb n="1577"/>Therefore depart, and leaue him heere with me.<lb n="1578" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I will not hence, and leaue my husband heere:<lb n="1579"/>And <seg type="homograph">ill</seg> it doth beseeme your holinesse<lb n="1580"/>To separate the husband and the wife.<lb n="1581"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ab.</speaker>
              <ab>Be quiet and depart, thou shalt not haue him.<lb n="1582"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Complaine vnto the Duke of this indignity.<lb n="1583"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Come go, I will fall prostrate at his feete,<lb n="1584"/>And neuer rise vntill my teares and prayers<lb n="1585"/>Haue won his grace to come in person hither,<lb n="1586"/>And take perforce my husband from the Abbesse.<lb n="1587"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>By this I thinke the Diall points at fiue:<lb n="1588"/>Anon I'me sure the Duke himselfe in person<lb n="1589"/>Comes this way to the melancholly vale;<lb n="1590"/>The place of depth, and sorrie execution,<lb n="1591"/>Behinde the ditches of the Abbey heere.<lb n="1592"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>Vpon what cause?<lb n="1593"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>To see a reuerent <hi rend="italic">Siracusian</hi> Merchant,<lb n="1594"/>Who put vnluckily into this Bay<lb n="1595"/>Against the Lawes and Statutes of this Towne,<lb n="1596"/>Beheaded publikely for his offence.<lb n="1597" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>See where  they come, we wil behold his death<lb n="1598" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Kneele to the Duke before he passe the Abbey.<lb n="1599"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter the Duke of Ephesus, and the Merchant of Siracuse<lb n="1600"/>bare head, with the Headsman, &amp; other<lb n="1601"/>Officers.</stage>
                        <lb n="1602"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Yet once againe proclaime it publikely,<lb n="1603"/>If any friend will pay the summe for him,<lb n="1604"/>He shall not die, so much we tender him.<lb n="1605" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Iustice most sacred Duke against the Abbesse.<lb n="1606"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>She is a vertuous and a reuerend Lady,<lb n="1607"/>It cannot be that she hath done thee wrong.<lb n="1608" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>May it please your Grace, <hi rend="italic">Antipholus</hi> my husba[n]d,<lb n="1609"/>Who I made Lord of me, and all I had,<lb n="1610"/>At your important Letters this <seg type="homograph">ill</seg> day,<lb n="1611"/>A most outragious fit of madnesse tooke him:<lb n="1612"/>That desp'rately he hurried through the streete,<lb n="1613"/>With him his bondman, all as mad as he,<lb n="1614"/>Doing displeasure to the Citizens,<lb n="1615"/>By rushing in their houses: bearing thence<lb n="1616"/>Rings, Iewels, any thing his rage did like.<lb n="1617"/>Once did I get him bound, and sent him home,<lb n="1618"/>Whil'st to take order for the wrongs I went,<lb n="1619"/>That heere and there his furie had committed,<lb n="1620"/>Anon I wot not, by what strong escape<lb n="1621"/>He broke from those that had the guard of him,<lb n="1622"/>And with his mad attendant and himselfe,<lb n="1623"/>Each one with irefull passion, with drawne swords<lb n="1624"/>Met vs againe, and madly bent on vs<lb n="1625"/>Chac'd vs away: till raising of more aide<lb n="1626"/>We came againe to binde them: then they fled<lb n="1627"/>Into this Abbey, whether we pursu'd them,<lb n="1628"/>And heere the Abbesse shuts the gates on vs,<lb n="1629"/>And will not suffer vs to fetch him out,<lb n="1630"/>Nor send him forth, that we may beare him hence.
      <pb n="I1v"/>
                        <lb n="1631"/>Therefore most gracious Duke with thy command,<lb n="1632"/>Let him be brought forth, and borne hence for helpe.<lb n="1633" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Long since thy husband seru'd me in my wars<lb n="1634"/>And I to thee ingag'd a Princes word,<lb n="1635"/>When thou didst make him Master of thy bed,<lb n="1636"/>To do him all the grace and good I could.<lb n="1637"/>Go some of you, knocke at the Abbey gate,<lb n="1638"/>And bid the Lady Abbesse come to me:<lb n="1639"/>I will determine this before I stirre.<lb n="1640"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter a Messenger.</stage>
                        <lb n="1641"/>Oh Mistris, Mistris, shift and saue your selfe,<lb n="1642"/>My Master and his man are both broke loose,<lb n="1643"/>Beaten the Maids a-row, and bound the Doctor,<lb n="1644"/>Whose beard they haue sindg'd off with brands of fire,<lb n="1645"/>And euer as it blaz'd, they threw on him<lb n="1646"/>Great pailes of puddled myre to quench the haire;<lb n="1647"/>My Mr preaches patience to him, and the while<lb n="1648"/>His man with Cizers nickes him like a foole:<lb n="1649"/>And sure (vnlesse you send some present helpe)<lb n="1650"/>Betweene them they will kill the Coniurer.<lb n="1651" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Peace foole, thy Master and his man are here,<lb n="1652"/>And that is false thou dost report to vs.<lb n="1653"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mess.</speaker>
              <ab>Mistris, vpon my life I tel you true,<lb n="1654"/>I haue not breath'd almost since I did see it.<lb n="1655"/>He cries for you, and vowes if he can take you,<lb n="1656"/>To scorch your face, and to disfigure you:<lb n="1657"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Cry within.</stage>
                        <lb n="1658"/>Harke, harke, I heare him Mistris: flie, be gone.<lb n="1659" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Come stand by me, feare nothing: guard with<lb n="1660"/>Halberds.<lb n="1661"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Ay me, it is my husband: witnesse you,<lb n="1662"/>That he is borne about inuisible,<lb n="1663"/>Euen now we hous'd him in the Abbey heere.<lb n="1664"/>And now he's there, past thought of humane reason.<lb n="1665"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter Antipholus, and E.<seg type="homograph">Dromio</seg> of Ephesus.</stage>
                        <lb n="1666" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Iustice most gracious Duke, oh grant me iu<seg type="hyphenatedCarryOver">stice</seg>,<lb n="1667"/>Euen for the seruice that long since I did thee,<lb n="1668"/>When I bestrid thee in the warres, and tooke<lb n="1669"/>Deepe scarres to saue thy life; euen for the blood<lb n="1670"/>That then I lost for thee, now grant me iustice.<lb n="1671" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.Fat.</speaker>
              <ab>Vnlesse the feare of death doth make me<lb n="1672"/>dote, I see my sonne <hi rend="italic">Antipholus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dromio.</hi>
                        <lb n="1673" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Iustice (sweet Prince) against <choice>
                     <orig>
                        <g ref="#ythat"/>
                     </orig>
                     <reg>that</reg>
                  </choice> Woman there:<lb n="1674"/>She whom thou gau'st to me to be my wife;<lb n="1675"/>That hath abused and dishonored me,<lb n="1676"/>Euen in the strength and height of iniurie:<lb n="1677"/>Beyond imagination is the wrong<lb n="1678"/>That she this day hath shamelesse throwne on me.<lb n="1679"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Discouer how, and thou shalt finde me iust.<lb n="1680" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>This day (great Duke) she shut the doores<lb n="1681"/>vpon me,<lb n="1682"/>While she with Harlots feasted in my house.<lb n="1683"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>A greeuous fault: say woman, didst thou so?<lb n="1684" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>No my good Lord. My selfe, he, and my sister,<lb n="1685"/>To day did dine together: so befall my soule,<lb n="1686"/>As this is false he burthens me withall.<lb n="1687"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Luc.</speaker>
              <ab>Nere may I looke on day, nor sleepe on night,<lb n="1688"/>But she tels to your Highnesse simple truth.<lb n="1689" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>O periur'd woman! They are both forsworne,<lb n="1690"/>In this the Madman iustly chargeth them.<lb n="1691"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>My Liege, I am aduised what I say,<lb n="1692"/>Neither disturbed with the effect of Wine,<lb n="1693"/>Nor headie-rash prouoak'd with raging ire,<lb n="1694"/>Albeit my wrongs might make one wiser mad.<lb n="1695"/>This woman lock'd me out this day from dinner;<lb n="1696"/>That Goldsmith there, were he not pack'd with her,<lb n="1697"/>Could witnesse it: for he was with me then,<lb n="1698"/>Who parted with me to go fetch a Chaine,<lb n="1699"/>Promising to bring it to the Porpentine,<lb n="1700"/>Where <hi rend="italic">Balthasar</hi> and I did dine together.<lb n="1701"/>Our dinner done, and he not comming thither,<lb n="1702"/>I went to seeke him. In the street I met him,<lb n="1703"/>And in his companie that Gentleman.<lb n="1704"/>There did this periur'd Goldsmith sweare me downe,<lb n="1705"/>That I this day of him receiu'd the Chaine,<lb n="1706"/>Which God he knowes, I saw not. For the which,<lb n="1707"/>He did arrest me with an Officer.<lb n="1708"/>I did obey, and sent my Pesant home<lb n="1709"/>For certaine Duckets: he with none return'd.<lb n="1710"/>Then fairely I bespoke the Officer<lb n="1711"/>To go in person with me to my house.<lb n="1712" rend="rj"/>By'th' way, we met my wife, her sister, and a rabble more<lb n="1713"/>Of vilde Confederates: Along with them<lb n="1714" rend="rj"/>They brought one <hi rend="italic">Pinch,</hi> a hungry leane-fac'd Villaine;<lb n="1715"/>A meere Anatomie, a Mountebanke,<lb n="1716"/>A thred-bare Iugler, and a Fortune-teller,<lb n="1717"/>A needy-hollow-ey'd-sharpe-looking-wretch;<lb n="1718"/>A liuing dead man. This pernicious slaue,<lb n="1719"/>Forsooth tooke on him as a Coniurer:<lb n="1720"/>And gazing in mine eyes, feeling my pulse,<lb n="1721"/>And with no-face (as 'twere) out-facing me,<lb n="1722"/>Cries out, I was possest. Then altogether<lb n="1723"/>They fell vpon me, bound me, bore me thence,<lb n="1724"/>And in a darke and dankish vault at home<lb n="1725"/>There left me and my man, both bound together,<lb n="1726"/>Till gnawing with my teeth my bonds in sunder,<lb n="1727"/>I gain'd my freedome; and immediately<lb n="1728"/>Ran hether to your Grace, whom I beseech<lb n="1729"/>To giue me ample satisfaction<lb n="1730"/>For these deepe shames, and great indignities.<lb n="1731" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>My Lord, in truth, thus far I witnes with him:<lb n="1732"/>That he din'd not at home, but was lock'd out.<lb n="1733"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>But had he such a Chaine of thee, or no?<lb n="1734"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>He had my Lord, and when he ran in heere,<lb n="1735"/>These people saw the Chaine about his necke.<lb n="1736" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Mar.</speaker>
              <ab>Besides, I will be sworne these eares of mine,<lb n="1737"/>Heard you confesse you had the Chaine of him,<lb n="1738"/>After you first forswore it on the Mart,<lb n="1739"/>And thereupon I drew my sword on you:<lb n="1740"/>And then you fled into this Abbey heere,<lb n="1741"/>From whence I thinke you are come by Miracle.<lb n="1742"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I neuer came within these Abbey wals,<lb n="1743"/>Nor euer didst thou draw thy sword on me:<lb n="1744"/>I neuer saw the Chaine, so helpe me heauen:<lb n="1745"/>And this is false you burthen me withall.<lb n="1746"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Why what an intricate impeach is this?<lb n="1747"/>I thinke you all haue drunke of <hi rend="italic">Circes</hi> cup:<lb n="1748"/>If heere you hous'd him, heere he would haue bin.<lb n="1749"/>If he were mad, he would not pleade so coldly:<lb n="1750"/>You say he din'd at home, the Goldsmith heere<lb n="1751"/>Denies that saying. Sirra, what say you?<lb n="1752" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Sir he din'de with her there, at the Porpen-<lb n="1753" type="inWord"/>tine. <lb n="1754"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>He did, and from my finger snacht that Ring.<lb n="1755"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Anti.</speaker>
              <ab>Tis true (my Liege) this Ring I had of her.<lb n="1756"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Saw'st thou him enter at the Abbey heere?<lb n="1757"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Curt.</speaker>
              <ab>As sure (my Liege) as I do see your Grace.<lb n="1758" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Why this is straunge: Go call the Abbesse hi-<lb n="1759" type="inWord"/>ther. <lb n="1760"/>I thinke you are all mated, or starke mad.
      <pb n="I2"/>
                        <lb n="1761"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exit one to the Abbesse.</stage>
                        <lb n="1762" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fa.</speaker>
              <ab>Most mighty Duke, vouchsafe me speak a word:<lb n="1763"/>Haply I see a friend will saue my life,<lb n="1764"/>And pay the sum that may deliuer me.<lb n="1765"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Speake freely <hi rend="italic">Siracusian</hi> what thou wilt.<lb n="1766"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fath.</speaker>
              <ab>Is not your name sir call'd <hi rend="italic">Antipholus</hi>?<lb n="1767"/>And is not that your bondman <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi>?<lb n="1768"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Within this houre I was his bondman sir,<lb n="1769"/>But he I thanke him gnaw'd in two my cords,<lb n="1770"/>Now am I <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> and his man, vnbound.<lb n="1771"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fath.</speaker>
              <ab>I am sure you both of you remember me.<lb n="1772"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Our selues we do remember sir by you:<lb n="1773"/>For lately we were bound as you are now.<lb n="1774"/>You are not <hi rend="italic">Pinches</hi> patient, are you sir?<lb n="1775" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Father.</speaker>
              <ab>Why looke you strange on me? you know<lb n="1776"/>me well.<lb n="1777"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I neuer saw you in my life till now.<lb n="1778" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fa.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh! griefe hath chang'd me since you saw me last,<lb n="1779"/>And carefull houres with times deformed hand,<lb n="1780"/>Haue written strange defeatures in my face:<lb n="1781"/>But tell me yet, dost thou not know my voice?<lb n="1782"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Neither.<lb n="1783"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fat.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> nor thou?<lb n="1784"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No trust me sir, nor I.<lb n="1785"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fa.</speaker>
              <ab>I am sure thou dost?<lb n="1786" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dromio.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <seg type="homograph">I</seg> sir, but I am sure I do not, and whatso-<lb n="1787" type="inWord"/>euer a man denies, you are now bound to beleeue him.<lb n="1788"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fath.</speaker>
              <ab>Not know my voice, oh times extremity<lb n="1789"/>Hast thou so crack'd and splitted my poore tongue<lb n="1790"/>In seuen short yeares, that heere my onely sonne<lb n="1791"/>Knowes not my feeble key of vntun'd cares?<lb n="1792"/>Though now this grained face of mine be hid<lb n="1793"/>In sap-consuming Winters drizled snow,<lb n="1794"/>And all the Conduits of my blood froze vp:<lb n="1795"/>Yet hath my night of life some memorie:<lb n="1796"/>My wasting lampes some fading glimmer left;<lb n="1797"/>My dull deafe eares a little vse to heare:<lb n="1798"/>All these old witnesses, I cannot erre.<lb n="1799"/>Tell me, thou art my sonne <hi rend="italic">Antipholus.</hi>
                        <lb n="1800"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I neuer saw my Father in my life.<lb n="1801"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fa.</speaker>
              <ab>But seuen yeares since, in <hi rend="italic">Siracusa</hi> boy<lb n="1802"/>Thou know'st we parted, but perhaps my sonne,<lb n="1803"/>Thou sham'st to acknowledge me in miserie.<lb n="1804"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>The Duke, and all that know me in the City,<lb n="1805"/>Can witnesse with me that it is not so.<lb n="1806"/>I ne're saw <hi rend="italic">Siracusa</hi> in my life.<lb n="1807"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>I tell thee <hi rend="italic">Siracusian,</hi> twentie yeares<lb n="1808"/>Haue I bin Patron to <hi rend="italic">Antipholus,</hi>
                        <lb n="1809"/>During which time, he ne're saw <hi rend="italic">Siracusa:</hi>
                        <lb n="1810"/>I see thy age and dangers make thee dote.<lb n="1811"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Enter the Abbesse with Antipholus Siracusa,<lb n="1812"/>and Dromio <seg type="homograph">Sir</seg>.</stage>
                        <lb n="1813" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Abbesse.</speaker>
              <ab>Most mightie Duke, behold a man much<lb n="1814"/>wrong'd.<lb n="1815"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">All gather to see them.</stage>
                        <lb n="1816"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I see two husbands, or mine eyes deceiue me.<lb n="1817"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>One of these men is <hi rend="italic">genius</hi> to the other:<lb n="1818"/>And so of these, which is the naturall man,<lb n="1819"/>And which the spirit? Who deciphers them?<lb n="1820"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dromio.</speaker>
              <ab>I Sir am <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> command him away.<lb n="1821"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>I Sir am <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> pray let me stay.<lb n="1822"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Egeon</hi> art thou not? or else his ghost.<lb n="1823" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Drom.</speaker>
              <ab>Oh my olde Master, who hath bound him<lb n="1824"/>heere?<lb n="1825"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Abb.</speaker>
              <ab>Who euer bound him, I will lose his bonds,<lb n="1826"/>And gaine a husband by his libertie:<lb n="1827"/>Speake olde <hi rend="italic">Egeon,</hi> if thou bee'st the man<lb n="1828"/>That hadst a wife once call'd <hi rend="italic">Aemilia,</hi>
                        <lb n="1829"/>That bore thee at a burthen two faire sonnes?<lb n="1830"/>Oh if thou bee'st the same <hi rend="italic">Egeon,</hi> speake:<lb n="1831"/>And speake vnto the same <hi rend="italic">Aemilia.</hi>
                        <lb n="1832"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Why heere begins his Morning storie right:<lb n="1833"/>These two <hi rend="italic">Antipholus,</hi> these two so like,<lb n="1834"/>And these two <hi rend="italic">Dromio's,</hi> one in semblance:<lb n="1835"/>Besides her vrging of her wracke at sea,<lb n="1836"/>These are the parents to these children,<lb n="1837"/>Which accidentally are met together.<lb n="1838"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Fa.</speaker>
              <ab>If I dreame not, thou art <hi rend="italic">Aemilia,</hi>
                        <lb n="1839"/>If thou art she, tell me, where is that sonne<lb n="1840"/>That floated with thee on the fatall rafte.<lb n="1841"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Abb.</speaker>
              <ab>By men of <hi rend="italic">Epidamium,</hi> he, and I,<lb n="1842"/>And the twin <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> all were taken vp;<lb n="1843"/>But <seg type="homograph">by</seg> and by, rude Fishermen of <hi rend="italic">Corinth</hi>
                        <lb n="1844"/>By force tooke <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> and my sonne from them,<lb n="1845"/>And me they left with those of <hi rend="italic">Epidamium.</hi>
                        <lb n="1846"/>What then became of them, I cannot tell:<lb n="1847"/>I, to this fortune that you see mee in.<lb n="1848"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Antipholus</hi> thou cam'st from <hi rend="italic">Corinth</hi> first.<lb n="1849"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>No sir, not I, I came from <hi rend="italic">Siracuse.</hi>
                        <lb n="1850" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>Stay, stand apart, I know not which is which.<lb n="1851" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I came from <hi rend="italic">Corinth</hi> my most gracious Lord<lb n="1852"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>And I with him.<lb n="1853" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>Brought to this Town by that most famous<lb n="1854"/>Warriour,<lb n="1855"/>Duke <hi rend="italic">Menaphon</hi> your most renowned Vnckle.<lb n="1856"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>Which of you two did dine with me to day?<lb n="1857"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I, gentle Mistris.<lb n="1858"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>And are not you my husband?<lb n="1859"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>No, I say nay to that.<lb n="1860"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>And so do I, yet did she call me so:<lb n="1861"/>And this faire Gentlewoman her sister heere<lb n="1862"/>Did call me brother. What I told you then,<lb n="1863"/>I hope I shall haue leisure to make good,<lb n="1864"/>If this be not a dreame I see and heare.<lb n="1865" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Goldsmith.</speaker>
              <ab>That is the Chaine sir, which you had of<lb n="1866"/>mee.<lb n="1867"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>I thinke it be sir, I denie it not.<lb n="1868"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>And you sir for this Chaine arrested me.<lb n="1869"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Gold.</speaker>
              <ab>I thinke I did sir, I deny it not.<lb n="1870"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Adr.</speaker>
              <ab>I sent you monie sir to be your baile<lb n="1871"/>By <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> but I thinke he brought it not.<lb n="1872"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>No, none by me.<lb n="1873"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>This purse of Duckets I receiu'd from you,<lb n="1874"/>And <hi rend="italic">Dromio</hi> my man did bring them me:<lb n="1875"/>I see we still did meete each others man,<lb n="1876"/>And I was tane for him, and he for me,<lb n="1877"/>And thereupon these errors are arose.<lb n="1878" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>These Duckets pawne I for my father heere.<lb n="1879"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>It shall not neede, thy father hath his life.<lb n="1880"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Cur.</speaker>
              <ab>Sir I must haue that Diamond from you.<lb n="1881" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>There take it, and much thanks for my good<lb n="1882"/>cheere.<lb n="1883" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Abb.</speaker>
              <ab>Renowned Duke, vouchsafe to take the paines<lb n="1884"/>To go with vs into the Abbey heere,<lb n="1885"/>And heare at large discoursed all our fortunes,<lb n="1886"/>And all that are assembled in this place:<lb n="1887"/>That by this simpathized one daies error<lb n="1888"/>Haue suffer'd wrong. Goe, keepe vs companie,
      <pb n="I2v"/>
                        <lb n="1889"/>And we shall make full satisfaction.<lb n="1890"/>Thirtie three yeares haue I but gone in trauaile<lb n="1891"/>Of you my sonnes, and till this present houre<lb n="1892"/>My heauie burthen are deliuered:<lb n="1893"/>The Duke my husband, and my children both,<lb n="1894"/>And you the Kalenders of their Natiuity,<lb n="1895"/>Go to a Gossips feast, and go with mee,<lb n="1896"/>After so long greefe such Natiuitie.<lb n="1897"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">Duke.</speaker>
              <ab>With all my heart, Ile Gossip at this feast.<lb n="1898"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt omnes. Manet the two Dromio's and<lb n="1899"/>two Brothers.</stage>
                        <lb n="1900" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Mast[er]. shall I fetch your stuffe from shipbord?<lb n="1901" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.An.</speaker>
              <ab>
                  <hi rend="italic">Dromio,</hi> what stuffe of mine hast thou imbarkt<lb n="1902" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Your goods that lay at host sir in the Centaur.<lb n="1903" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Ant.</speaker>
              <ab>He speakes to me, I am your master <hi rend="italic">Dromio.</hi>
                        <lb n="1904"/>Come go with vs, wee'l looke to that anon,<lb n="1905"/>Embrace thy brother there, reioyce with him.  <stage rend="italic">Exit</stage>
                        <lb n="1906"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>There is a fat friend at your masters house,<lb n="1907"/>That kitchin'd me for you to day at dinner:<lb n="1908"/>She now shall be my sister, not my wife,<lb n="1909" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.D.</speaker>
              <ab>Me thinks you are my glasse, &amp; not my brother:<lb n="1910"/>I see by you, I am a sweet-fac'd youth,<lb n="1911"/>Will you walke in to see their gossipping?<lb n="1912"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Not I sir, you are my elder.<lb n="1913"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>That's a question, how shall we trie it.<lb n="1914" rend="rj"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">S.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Wee'l draw Cuts for the Signior, till then,<lb n="1915"/>lead thou first.<lb n="1916"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
            <sp>
              <speaker rend="italic">E.Dro.</speaker>
              <ab>Nay then thus:<lb n="1917"/>We came into the world like brother and brother:<lb n="1918" rend="rj"/>And now let's go hand in hand, not one before another.<lb n="1919"/>
                        <stage rend="italic">Exeunt.</stage>
                        <lb n="1920"/>
                     </ab>
            </sp>
          </div>
        </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

